alan edelman and philip the corgi and
we're here to talk to you
about abstraction abstraction has an
opposite specialization
it's all about what's the same and
what's different for different
kinds of things different
types of elements so
let's get the idea by let's
put i'll call it element
just an arbitrary name
let me say element is equal to one okay
and let's go ahead and put this element
in an array let's
fill up oh i don't know let's fill up
an array with three
rows and four columns
with this element and
here you see a three by four
array or matrix with the number one now
let's take a close look you see
the information that julia gives back is
that it's a three by four array
it's the number two says it's two
dimensional so one would
be a vector two would be
a matrix perhaps and three would be
maybe they call it a tensor or a
three-dimensional array
and the elements are in
64s and just to be clear
if i take the type of the element
that's the julia command it'll tell you
that it's an int
64. now we can go ahead and change
things for example we
could make the element 1.0
okay and now look i've got a 3x4 array
of floats 64s now so that 1.0
is a float type it's a two-dimensional
array still but it's filled with floats
maybe we should kind of um keep track
of the numbers that we're putting in so
let's or at least how about we keep
track of the types
so the type of one the type of 1.0
let's put this itself into an array
and you could see here oh let's make it
actually a vector i'll put a comma and
it'll make it a vector
okay and you can see here that
we have an int64 and a float 64.
and if you wanted to know what is the
type of keep track
since it's displayed a little bit
differently you could
see that the internal
julia is that it's an array it's one
dimensional and the elements are
datatypes so let's
go a little bit further
and change the element to a string let's
take the string
for one okay and my
assistant looks like he has to
go somewhere all right so now we have
this is this is the type of the element
as a string
and we have a three by
four array of the string
one so let's add that
as well to our vector
just so that we could keep track so you
see we have integers we
have we have floats and we
have strings and the
whole idea is that
a computer language shouldn't require
any difference between these different
data types here i'll show you another
one let's use a rational
number so we can go
uh 1 divided by one
is two slashes and julia
so that's our element and here's the
three by four array of
and this may be a little bit interesting
it's still the number
two it's two dimensional
but it consists of rationals that are
themselves made of int64s and so
this is a type that's
made up of other types
a composite type if you will a rational
made up of int64s
okay so let's put that one in here too
and you see we get type
of one and we'll add
that to our list as well
okay so we have ins float strings
rational now let me stand back a second
and point out that at some level
to you these might all be the number one
right in some representation
there's one 1.0 the string one
one slash one you could
even think of one in
different human languages
like uno in spanish
or um the way one writes one with like
to me it looks like a dash in chinese
right and so all of these are
representations of the
abstract notion of one
on a computer of course uh concretely
every one of these is represented
in a different way somehow even if we
think of it all as one
we could go a little further we can
actually go looking for a picture of the
number now i'm gonna
look for some images
of one and them look
nice oh this one's fun
here's a cute number one download
this uh yeah i just got the url i don't
have to really look
at it the the the pkg.add
only needed to happen once so it's
actually tempting to put a comment here
and a comment here
okay but we do need to load the images
package there it is we've got it
so now this should work there we go and
there's that cute little picture of a
one how do you like that
okay and let's while we're at it let's
um what should we call
it should we call it a uh
how about a cute acute one
all right it's a cute_one image so we'll
just store it in cute_one
and so now what we can do is and this is
kind of fun i can go
ahead and edit this and call
this a cute one you see
and you'll see that i now have a three
by four array of images
isn't that nice now uh so you see
just by changing the type it it goes and
does something a little bit
different but a little bit the same and
imagine what would happen
if my element itself was an array so for
example suppose my
element was the array one
two three four what's
going to happen now
well let's think about that for a moment
so my elements one two three
four and so now i
have an array of arrays
and you can see how the
nesting is sort of logical
uh the it's a two-dimensional array
whose elements themselves
are two-dimensional arrays whose
elements themselves are
int64. they're integers so it displays
it in a sort of compact format you might
like that or you may not
but you can see that
the elements are arrays of
int64s so it kind of makes sense
that we could actually add that as well
so if i have the type
of and i put in the one two three
four you'll see that
i now have arrays as element types
all right let's go further
now and make an array
of this cute uh what's
it called cute one
and let that be the element and let's
take a closer look we have my
three by four array of these images
and let's take a look
the type of the element
is itself an array of colors
so let's get this straight we have an
array of images what's an image an image
is an array of colors
so it's an array of an array of colors
right a color by the way is itself a
composite type
it's in rgba red green blue alpha alpha
being the opacity
of some unsigned integers that are norms
in some way you see and
so i'd like to sum this up
by saying that the
notion of an array
is a container it's a
container that contains
elements and the elements could be of
many very different types
and soon we're going to see that one can
write functions
on arrays and if all goes well these
functions should be
independent of the type of the element
in other words if you
wanted to move things around
or you wanted to manipulate an array it
shouldn't care
about the type of the element as long as
it makes sense so now
you have the notion of
abstraction