hi i'm just reminiscing about one of my
early versions of image theme
written probably around six years ago
here you can see this data center this
is where the
mit computer science and ai lab building
lives
and in my family this building was
always called
the broken building because when my 20
year old son was just a little little
boy maybe he was
four years old the building was opening
and
he said dad this building looks broken
and so we always called it the broken
building
but what you see of course is that the
the building has so many nice edges and
so as you sort of let the lightning go
by you can see how it
kind of sometimes follows some of these
edges and that's a lot of fun
so regarding this problem set it was
inspired by a problem set over at brown
this is cs019 from 2014
where they basically kind of spell out
how students could implement this
algorithm and by now you've probably
heard that this algorithm
is was designed to be useful for being
able to resize
images for different modalities like
telephones or tv sets
so that you know projector screens so
that you can
not have to sort of distort with
different aspect ratios
so how did i first learn about this well
interestingly enough back in 2014 and i
just took up this email
so this email is from six years ago one
of my computer science colleagues
invited me to come down and they were
looking at different languages
python julia other languages for
introductory computer science classes
and probably at the time the clip julia
wasn't quite ready for an introductory
cs class
now of course julia's really been taking
off
so they didn't use julie at the time but
we had a lot of fun talking about
what we might do with you know with
julia in such a class
and one of the things that came up was
that python was really insufficient
for being able to do this imaging
algorithm they ended up using lots of
very very small images in fact
i put the images here that that was
being used in the class and you could
see these
very small images there's the bell
carving the bangalore dancers the
british museum
right and the chagall picture that these
pictures were
were tiny because if you make them small
then you wouldn't need so much time or
power to be able to
to do the image scene algorithm and even
back in the day i said that's silly just
use julia
it'll be perfectly fast so and you're
going to be the beneficiary of all of
that