this week we are going to be talking
about an algorithm for resizing an image
but without resizing the
objects within it so i've skipped all
the way to the bottom of a notebook that
you're going to go through this week
and what you'll see is we've got this
very famous image the persistence of
memory
on the left all the melting clocks and
then on the right is going to be a
squished version of it
and based on how i tweak this slider we
can squish it to be narrower and
narrower
but if you'll notice even as i get it to
be about half the width that it was
before
the clocks themselves haven't actually
changed their width nor has this
weird monster looking creature instead
the algorithm is smart enough to kind of
kill the dead space
inside the image without killing any of
the content and if you contrast this
with how you know a lot of design
software
handles things if i were to open up you
know illustrator and i take the same
image and i say i want to
rescale it i want to make it half the
width it squishes all of the contents
inside it sort of deforms it
other pieces of design software actually
have different defaults so if i were to
go to
figma for example and i take the same
same image and i say okay let's try to
rescale it what it defaults to doing
is cropping it so it'll take out some of
the content on the left edge
but if you want to somehow get the best
of both worlds where you're not getting
rid of anything on the inside
but you're not deforming anything on the
inside this tactic which is called seam
carving
is kind of a shockingly effective way to
do that
so i'm going to give the high level view
of how this algorithm works in this
lecture and start to go through a bit of
this notebook kind of from the bottom to
the top
at first and as the week progresses with
the other lectures we're really going to
dig into the code
for how this is possible so the first
step
i'm going to go ahead and change what's
displayed here to give a little inkling
of what's going on
on the right you'll notice these sort of
pink lightning bolts what's happening is
that with each step
as we're making the image smaller the
algorithm decides on
a seam to remove from the image so this
is a set of pixels where there's one
pixel per row
that forms this continuous path from the
top to the bottom
and it has to somehow decide what path
is the one that's most okay to get rid
of
so you'll notice right here it's this
path that's avoiding the branch it's
avoiding the clock
but it's just going through the sky in
the ground and it's saying that's
probably something that we can cut out
and it keeps the image looking largely
the same and as i keep shrinking it
further and further it's choosing these
other seams which look like these pink
lightning bolts
so question is of course you know how do
we find that what is it actually doing
and the tactic here is going to be to
assign some kind of importance to each
of the pixels in the screen
and then find the path from the top to
the bottom
which passes through the least important
pixels or if we would have you know a
number associated with that importance
as you add up that number from top to
bottom it should be minimizing that
total quantity
and there's different approaches that
you can take and the original paper on
this describes several different ones
but what we're going to do in
conjunction with what we were talking
about last week
is a kind of edge detection so skipping
up higher in the notebook here we've got
the same image on the left
and on the right you'll notice that
we've pulled out all of the edges into
this really
kind of pretty looking pencil sketch
view and what we're going to say is that
the importance of a pixel
is going to be the extent to which it
sits inside an edge so all of the white
ones that we see on the right here
would be considered important they
shouldn't be cut out but anything black
so you notice that's coming from the sky
it's coming from the ground
all of that where there's not any sharp
edges those are the pixels that we're
okay removing
now in the last lecture on convolutions
i touched just a tiny bit on edge
detection with sobel filters
but let me switch to another notebook
here to go into a little bit more detail
on that
so i've got a very simple image here
which is just a white blob in a blue
background
and what we're going to want to do is
somehow pick up on all of the edges
which
should just form a circle around it in
this cell here i'm looking at the kernel
library and i'm calling sobel
which if you'll remember pulls out two
little three by three arrays
so if we were to just look at the raw
data for one of those arrays the one
that i'm naming s
x and you'll see it's a three by three
array it's got
values zero down the center column and
then positive values on the right
negative values on the left
and if we just pull up a simple function
to visualize that
we're looking at it as blue on the right
and red on the left
and if we look at the other one sy
same deal but it's just kind of pulling
out from the top and the bottom
and now let's say we were to do a
convolution with one of these filters so
maybe i'll take this one in the x
direction
so a simple three by three grid and i'm
going to do this convolution against the
blob image at the top
which as you might remember from last
lecture means we sort of take this
kernel and have it walk across every
pixel
and take a weighted sum what we end up
getting is something that produces
positive values wherever the uh blob
image was fading from bright towards
darker
and then negative values where it was
fading from dark towards bright
and if that seems like the opposite of
what you might expect thinking of this
kernel remember that with convolutions
we actually think of
turning that kernel upside down before
it marches across and again this was all
in the last lecture if you want to
look at that with more detail now
instead if we were to
filter it with the other one the one
that was
in the y direction and if i go and
change what's going on down here
we see that it picks up on the top and
the bottom
now i actually want to visualize this in
a slightly different way so what i'm
going to do
is let me go ahead and hide this cell
and i will also get rid of this cell
here let's look back at the kernel in
the x direction
and then what i'm going to do is look at
a bunch of little vectors on the screen
that indicate
how strong is the convolution of this
image
with that kernel at various points and
then it gives a little direction to it
so
at points where the convolution pops out
positive
it'll be vectors pointing to the right
and where it pops out negative its
vectors pointing to the left
and then if i were to do this in the y
direction which would correspond to
convolving with that
s y kernel same deal basically anywhere
where that convolution is positive it'll
be vectors this time pointing
up and otherwise pointing down and then
the main idea here is going to be to
add those two vectors together so if i
were to just take the ones pointed to
the
uh right so just the ones pointed to the
right and i add them with the ones that
are just pointing up
what we get are these ones that are
pointing away from the brightness
towards the darkness
and any of you familiar with
multivariable calculus might find this
very familiar notion it's something
known as the gradient where if you have
a vector
that has an x component telling you how
much
a value changes as you move from the
left to the right which we might call
the partial derivative with respect to x
and then the y component tells you how
much you change as you move
up and down the partial derivative with
respect to y
when you package those together it gets
you a vector that points
kind of in the direction of greatest
change so
often it's described as the direction of
steepest ascent
and actually in that sense i should be
honest that the vectors that you're
seeing right now are technically in the
negative direction of the gradient
because the gradient proper goes from
the low values towards the high it'll
point from low to high
and this is doing the opposite for our
purposes the direction actually won't
matter that much
all that we're going to care about is
the magnitude of the vectors that we're
looking at
and the reason that it's defaulting to
this is just because
when you do the convolution with a sobo
filter it flips that filter around first
so it's sort of doing
the negative of what you might expect
for the reasons that you know i talked
about last lecture
now while we're here it might be worth
really digging into why this particular
filter this
shape of values is a reasonable way to
try to measure something like
a derivative you know a partial
derivative in the x direction or in the
y direction
so if we go over and we just picture a
grid of values
let's say we want to understand the rate
of change around the pixels surrounding
what i've labeled as
e here the first dead simple thing you
might think to do if you want to know
what's the rate of change
in the x direction is to just look at
the value of that pixel
f and then subtract off the value of
pixel e
and honestly that would probably work
you could have an incredibly simple
kernel that was just adding up the value
to the right subtracting the one to the
left and that would get you some notion
of a partial derivative
but if you want more of the information
in what's going on you might also
want to maybe average this or simply add
it to the difference between e and d
you know what's the change between this
pixel and what's happening just to the
left of it
so we might add on you know the
difference between e and d
and potentially divide the whole thing
by two or average it it doesn't really
matter in absolute terms
all we care about at the end is the
relative terms what's the relative
change
uh around one pixel compared to the
amount of change around another
and if you look at this of course we can
just cancel out the minus e and the plus
e going on
so it's just taking this right value
minus the left one
and again that would probably work
pretty well as an edge detecting filter
if all you did
was take that f minus d but with the
sobel filter effectively what you're
doing is
taking a kind of average with what's
going on on the top row and the bottom
row we're at the top you know we would
be taking the same deal but
the corresponding terms are c and a here
and at the bottom it would look like
i and g and really what a simple filter
does is it gives more weight to this
middle one
since after all that's where the pixel
we care about is so it gives kind of
half weight to the ones on the top and
bottom and then more weight to that
middle one
and if you unpack what this is really
saying in terms of where you add and
where you subtract
it gets you exactly this shape that
we were calling sx over here and if you
just look at its values
it's exactly what i just described
you're taking in that middle row
something on the right minus the part on
the leftmost
and then the top and bottom rows do the
same but scale down by a little bit
the whole point here though is that when
we use those sobo filters to get a
notion of partial derivative in the x
partial derivative in the y
and that gets us a gradient vector if we
just look at the magnitude of that
gradient vector
and i'm going to plot it down here where
white means a higher magnitude black
means a lower magnitude
what we've done is picked up on the edge
of this
circular blob and this becomes a little
bit more interesting if we
take something that's different than the
disc and we have you know another very
pixelated image like mario in here
so here again we're doing the same thing
where we have all of the rates of change
in the x direction we're adding them to
all of the rates of change in the y
direction
and then if we just look at the
magnitude of those gradient vectors
it picks up on the edginess of mario and
more than that it tells us that the
brightest pixels are the ones where
there's a really sharp edge
and then the ones that are kind of a
lighter gray are an edge but
ones that don't correspond to as much
contrast
now digging into the code for what this
is actually displaying
you'll notice that i've got a del x and
del y
being defined as the partial derivatives
of this image
and that partial derivative function as
i've kind of been describing
is basically just applying sobel filters
it takes the
sx and sy the kernel.sobole that we were
just looking at
and depending on what i have toggled
here it will populate the del x term to
be a convolution
of the brightness of the image with the
sobo filter in the x direction
and then the del y term is a convolution
of that brightness but with the other
filter
so that's all the partial derivative
functions are doing but this is just a
nice abstraction so that we don't have
to think of the convolution necessarily
and you know if i have both of my
buttons toggled here to say yes we're
taking into account the x and the y
direction
what it does is it basically just takes
the magnitude of that vector
you know it takes the del x direction
squared the del y direction
squared and then the square root of all
of that that
is going to be the notion of importance
that we assign to each one of our pixels
so jumping back to our salvador dali
example
that's exactly what's going on with the
image on the right and if i open up a
little under the hood here
you can see that we're pulling out these
two different kernels the sobo filters
we are taking a convolution in this case
with the brightness of the image
and then taking the square root of the
sum of the squares of those values
that's what's determining the the value
of each pixel
and if we scroll up a little bit we can
see kind of all of that broken down a
little bit more
this image on the left is the
convolution with the sx filter
the one on the right is the convolution
with the sy filter so kind of the
edginess in the x direction edginess in
the right direction
but thinking back to our end goal here
which is the
really clever way to shrink down an
image by cutting out the unimportant
seams
this still leaves an open question of
what's the best way to find that seam
from the top to the bottom
find some path from the top to the
bottom which we consider to be passing
through the least important of all the
pixels
well for that again let me shift to a
smaller example that might be a little
bit easier to think about
okay so here i've got a grid and i've
associated a value with each
element in that grid and let's say i
want to start at this one which is 0.3
and i want to find a path to the bottom
that passes through the
the lowest valued pixels now one
approach might be a greedy algorithm
where we look at the three below it and
this is going to be our notion of
connectedness is that each pixel has to
be
connected to one of the three below it
you can't jump more than that we can
talk more about what might happen if you
try
but if we take a greedy approach you
would just choose the one that's the
lowest value so in this case it would
choose the
the pixel with value zero and then we
look at the three below that it would
choose the one with 0.2
the three below that the smallest is 0.4
and we continue on like that and this
would be sort of
a greedy algorithm way of finding a seam
down the image
where the total value of all the pixels
that it touches is pretty low
and in this case if we add them all up
it ends up being 1.3
but the problem with greedy algorithms
like this is that
you can't be sure that you've actually
found the best seam from the top to the
bottom
and in fact for this example it's not
the best and we can see that with
another much less efficient approach
where we search through all possible
paths from the top to the bottom
and then we consider the sum of the
values that it passes through each one
and we're just going to keep track of
which one is the lowest after searching
through them all
so here it searched through them all in
this small example there were around i
think 200 examples it had to search
through
and it found one that isn't the greedy
algorithm notice as it goes from the
first pixel from the first row down to
the next row it doesn't take the
smallest choice it takes that 0.1
because that gives it access to much
lower values on the way down
and here it was a total of 0.6 in
contrast
to the 1.3 that we had from the other
example
but if you start to think about
computational complexity on doing a
tactic like this where we're searching
through
every possible path from the top to the
bottom remember
each step involves three different
choices so you're taking
basically 3 to the power n where n is
the number of rows
that's going to be on the order of the
number of steps that you have to take
which for any reasonably sized image is
going to be completely untenable
but if we notice what's actually going
on here there's a lot of repeated
computation in doing all of these
so for example while it's searching
through these paths you know on this one
it has to add up
0.3 plus 0.0 plus 0.4 plus 0.0
on and on and then on the next one it
takes
pretty much the same sum but it's only
changing that last part
and then on the next step it again has
pretty much the same sum for the
beginning
with just changes at the end so going
through all of these and redoing that
sum
every single time is clearly pretty
inefficient there is a lot of room for
improvement here
so the actual algorithm that we're going
to use which falls into a family of what
we might call dynamic programming
will make an effort to memorize some of
the sums that it needs along the way
so that it doesn't have to recompute
things needlessly
so pulling up the very last animation
here before we jump back to the notebook
i'm going to have that grid of values on
the left and for lack of a better term
some people often just call these
values the energy so we're trying to
find a path of minimal energy
and on the right the goal is going to be
to populate this in a way where
each value will tell us the minimum
possible total energy
of some path towards the bottom so for
example
this 1.7 at the top is telling us no
matter what path we choose to get
towards the bottom
it has to have a total energy of at
least 1.7
so you know maybe it involves taking
this 0.4 plus 0.4 plus 0.2
on and on it's something that's
relatively high whereas
this little value here this 0.3 tells us
there's some path from this pixel
towards the bottom
where the sum cumulative energy is 0.3
and looking over at the corresponding
point we can probably see what that path
is it's this 0.1 plus 0 plus 0 plus 0
plus 0.2 now as far as how we actually
form this we do it from the bottom to
the top
so the first step is going to be to
simply copy that bottom row
since once you're at the bottom that's
the best that you can do whatever the
energy of the pixel that you're on
that's going to be the minimal total
path and then for each pixel above it
all we do is say what's the smallest
number below you
and then i'm going to add the new energy
of the new pixel that i'm on
plus the minimal energy below it
so you know maybe i'll scoot over to a
more interesting example like this one
where it's got three possible energies
below it point two point five and point
three
obviously the step that it would choose
to take is to get to that point two
and to get the new cumulative energy we
take the energy of that corresponding
pixel which is point two and that gives
us that point four
and so that's how we fill out that row
and then we do precisely the same thing
for the next row
so let me jump to another maybe
interesting
this is a sufficiently interesting pixel
so this one
we see that it's got three choices for
where to hop below it
and now it's not looking at the energy
of the pixels below it but it's saying
it once i get to that pixel below me
what's going to be the sum
total energy of the minimal path to the
bottom from there
so in this case the best option would be
this point two and then we add that to
the value of the pixel which is
zero and we get that point two so we
keep doing this iteratively on the way
up
and what it means is the number of steps
required
is just three times the total number of
pixels in the image
which is dramatically better than the
three to the end that we were getting by
doing the
uh exhaustive global search the
inefficient way
but this still gives us a way of finding
the globally optimum choice for a path
from the top to the bottom
because for example let's say i'm
starting from the
pixel we were looking at earlier this
0.31
all i have to do is look at that and
with each step on the way down
simply go to the lowest so i go to the
lowest neighbor here that 0.3
the lowest neighbor there that 0.2 and
keep doing that
and what i'll find is a minimal path
which you'll notice that 0.6 should be
familiar from
what our globally exhaustive search
doing it the inefficient way ended up
finding
after it looked through all of them and
did all of these computations it sniffed
out the one that was
in fact total energy 0.6 so that's what
we might call the dynamic programming
approach where it's kind of keeping
track of values on the way not having to
redo computations
and let's see what it looks like in the
context of our notebook so what we're
going to do is look at each pixel
and ask hey what is the path with least
total
energy towards the bottom and in this
context what we mean by energy is the
edginess of that pixel measured with the
gradient like i was just describing
so if you say hey what's the uh minimal
total energy for some path from
this particular pixel towards the bottom
and then you assign it a color
this is what we get so just to be clear
this image right here is kind of the
scaled up version
in the context of the melting clocks
image of what we were building up in a
much smaller example
over here from bottom to top where the
pixels which are increasingly teal
are the ones that don't really have a
good path from the top to the bottom
so to speak so over here in our notebook
everything which is a really bright
pixel
is kind of screaming out do not touch me
if you have a seam that ends up where i
am right now
there's going to be no way towards the
bottom that doesn't involve cutting out
things that we want to keep
so if we you know compare this to the
actual image that we have
you'll notice that we get these kind of
triangle shapes above all of the content
so above the strange monster creature
here
we have these triangles which is a way
of saying don't let a scene get into
this point
because once it gets there any path
towards the bottom of the image
will have to pass through something
which is full of edges something which
has high energy something that we don't
want to get rid of
you'll be going through more of the
implementation details in the next
lecture with a live coding session
featuring the great the one and only
james schloss
but for right now let's actually take a
little bit of a peek behind the hood to
see what's going on in generating this
this array of values which again is
exactly what we were looking at
with this animation over here where
we're kind of going from the bottom to
the top
thinking term by term building up values
based on
just adding the energy of a given pixel
with whatever the
minimal term sitting right below it was
but let's let's think through that in
more detail
so we've got this function here which is
trying to find the uh
the least edgy path you know the least
edgy values
for a given array of energies or
edginess or whatever we want to consider
e to represent here so we start by
creating array of zeros with the same
size
and then we're also actually going to
keep track of the directions so
what direction should we step from each
pixel to get to that optimal path
that actually makes it so that we can
draw one of these seams
now if you'll remember the very first
step before we did any of the
recursive looks was to copy whatever the
bottom row in the energy matrix was
over to this new one that we're
generating and so that's exactly what we
do here we take
whatever that bottom row is for e and we
fill that into the least e matrix
from there we have a loop that goes from
the bottom to the top and then we're
going to go from the left to the right
and essentially what we're doing here is
we're just finding the minimal value
from the least e matrix that we've
already been building
and then we add that together with the
corresponding energy value
of the of the original matrix and then
what we're also doing is keeping track
of the directions
so for example if we were to pop over
here and we imagine while we're
populating this
you know we're populating let's say yeah
this pixel here
so it looks at the 3 below it it sees
that 0.2
is the smallest one we want to remember
that that's the direction it's going to
walk
and so here we're going to assign an
index of negative 1 0
and 1 for the three possible directions
that you can step as you go down
and we're filling out this matrix of
directions what we're calling dirs and
what this line says is essentially fill
it either with a negative one a zero or
a one
depending on what the minimal value that
we found was
so once we've built up this matrix of
directions we could actually
visualize it with a bunch of little
arrows if you wanted so this is what
comes out from
a sub-portion of the salvador dali image
where we're stepping either a little bit
tone to the left a little bit down
in the pure direction or down to the
right and that effectively is the same
as having seams for
our image so over here we've got another
little slider
which is basically telling us what is
the best possible seam
from a given pixel on the top towards
the bottom and it's using that
directions matrix
and you'll notice on the right what it's
passing through are all of the
darkest pixels right it's the ones that
involve low energy so as we kind of play
with the slider and walk it across
it's showing us the best paths from top
to bottom that hit low energy pixels
which again
means hitting ones that don't have edges
which is the metric that we're using for
whether or not we want to include a
pixel and so that
effectively is the algorithm once you
have these seams you choose the seam
with the smallest possible energy
and with each step you snip that out of
the image
and as you snip more and more of them
out we get a narrower and narrower image
but it's kept all of the content
now this works particularly well for our
melting clocks image but i want to show
you an example
where this fails what are the times
where cutting out the
non-edgy pixels might not actually give
us something that's
visually what we're going for so i think
one good example here would be
looking at starry night because just
based on the style of this painting
all of the stuff in the background
pretty much all of the things in the
image
are edges there's a lot of changing in
color as you move a little bit from
point to point
and we can see this when we do our two
different filters and compute our two
different gradients
in this case it's just tons of edges
left and right
and when we put them together to get our
pencil sketch we see that
the background you know the sky is full
of
whiteness it's full of high energy
things that we would potentially
not want to remove so when we build up
that matrix with our dynamic programming
approach that says
what should i not be touching almost
everything in the sky in that actual
background
it seems to want to avoid and the one
region that it seems okay going through
is what actually sits more in the
foreground of the image this
sort of bush figure and when we actually
apply the seam carving
you can see that in action we can see
how
the slices that it wants to take out
disproportionately include that dark
foreground image simply because it has
fewer edges than a lot of the things in
the background
so for something like this the
performance it still produces something
pretty but maybe it's a little bit less
impressive if our goal is
not to distort the objects within the
image but that doesn't mean this whole
algorithm is out the window what it
means is that
the energy function that you're
assigning the way that you're putting
importance to each pixel might need to
change but then you can apply the same
basic idea of finding seams
using this dynamic programming approach
and cutting them out step by step
now just to finish things off i wanted
to show you a couple interesting points
from the original paper
on this on this topic this idea of seam
carving
you might wonder what happens if instead
of finding a nice seam from the top to
the bottom
you just choose the lowest energy pixel
from each row you know potentially that
should take out
an even less interesting subset of the
image as you carve down
but if you do that what you end up
getting is what's in this
image e here where it shifts all of the
things left to right so it doesn't
actually keep the objects intact at all
you might also wonder if instead of
choosing the seam which is able to step
either down and to the left down or down
into the right
if you just choose the columns which are
the least interesting the least edgy
and in that context what you get is
something that again it kind of looks
okay but you have these
strange artifacts along the way that
make it pretty clear that you've messed
with the image somehow
but i think the most fun thing from this
paper was when they talked about
potentially extending it where let's say
you
have some kind of image where you want
to get rid of part of it
and in this example presumably this was
someone's ex-girlfriend or something
like that and he wants to
remove that part of the image well if
you have any kind of
user interface that lets you manually
assign low importance to some of the
pixels
which is to say low energy to some of
the pixels so you might go and
manually decide which part you want to
remove and maybe assign high energy to
parts that you want to keep like the
original
person in here then if you do that same
seam carving idea and you shrink the
image down
it will get rid of the specific
subsection of the image that you want it
to
and still leave it looking pretty
similar it doesn't really seem like
there was a sharp cut that happened in
this one
which i found kind of an interesting
application
okay so that's it for today and then in
some of the other lectures you're going
to look into
more of the implementation details
behind this and also how to make it run
as efficiently as you can where's the
low-hanging fruit there