the topic
of this segment is gpus
graphical processing units i'm going to
show
an example of doing a convolution using
a gpu in julia
so the actual application is probably
not
particularly important but we are going
to
take this julia logo right here and
we're going to
blur it so here's the logo you can see
it being blurred
right but that's not the important part
probably the important part is to
see for yourselves the power of a gpu so
i'm going to demonstrate this
in julia right here let's focus on the
time
i'm going to compare a cpu code with a
gpu code
so let's go ahead here and execute the
blurring on a cpu
and it took 257 milliseconds
let's just do it again just to see oh
it's about the same yep always about
you know 256 257 milliseconds
now i'm going to run the very same code
same blurring
i'm going to do it on a gpu okay and so
look at that two milliseconds 2.2
milliseconds
so oh that was a little bit more 45 but
that seemed to be a fluke 2.2
2.2 so about 2 milliseconds usually
and do you see that it's 100 times
faster on the gpu than the cpu
so what's going on here what's this all
about and
what is the research problem that
julia's trying to solve
well let me start with that second
question so with julia
we're trying to make it that you don't
have to learn a new language
to be able to run on a gpu so this is
the code portability problem
and it's pretty much a holy grail of
high performance computing computer
science
that the user just decides where the
data is going to live
and the very same code that calculates
the convolution
should just work these aren't library
calls these are actual functions that
are written
somewhere here down here i can try to
find it if you'll give me a chance to
look for it
so here's the convolved 2d function and
this function this is the basic math of
a convolution you take the
data you multiply point wise by a filter
and you add it all
up okay we can look a little bit at the
end of this segment
what some of the specifics of the julia
implementation are doing it's pretty
simple really though
there may be some commands that might
look a little funny but basically
if you want to do a convolved 2d you
just simply apply this
cu function cu stands for cuda which is
the
nvidia language for doing gpu
computations
that you take the cu you just that will
put
the image on the gpu
the filter is the same filter and the
range that's going to be the interior
part of indices
will also send over the gpu for a
convenience and then we're just going to
run the code
i didn't do it over here because i
wanted to not
count the timing for the movement just
for the computation but it's the same
basic idea
so let's step back a second talk about
gpus
gpus are made by a number of
manufacturers i guess
i think it's fair to say that the nvidia
gpu
is probably one of the most popular ones
right
now the uh nvidia here's some pictures
of
i just googled the pictures of nvidia
gpus
gpu started out life being particularly
useful
for gaming for graphics processing hence
the name
somewhere along the line people realize
that the very same
horsepower that's needed to computate
for
graphics turns out to be really really
useful for certain kinds of computations
and specifically it's very regular
computations
so for those of you know about matrices
matrix multiply
is something that gpus can do really
really fast so if you're multiplying
little matrices
and lots of them this is the sort of
thing that for example is happening in
machine learning algorithms
then gpus just really scream and then
answer very popular
for ai applications convolutions are
have a very similar character they're
very regular
i suppose you could imagine that if you
had
not a computer but you had a bunch of
people and you asked them to each
convolve an image
you could easily kind of choreograph the
various people that you have because it
is
so parallelizable so regular so easy
that's where the gpus shine they don't
do very well at general purpose
computations
and that's where the cpu kind of has the
advantage but when you have these
very very regular computationally
intensive
computations then the gpu does very well
so nvidia
is is one major manufacturer uh the amd
is another one i just googled amd gpus
and
here are some pictures of the kinds of
boards that have come up and
intel is very much in the act with the
laptops and
here you can see some intel gpus so
these various gpus are
what's accelerating ai and lots of other
numerical applications
so let me get back here to this code i
said i would kind of show you a few
aspects to this code i didn't really
want to go
into great depth but let me just mention
that we use a few
things for example uh julia has a
cartesian index
function so that you could directly
index into arrays with indices minus two
and minus one and zero
so here's a kind of five by three window
centered at zero
zero and i think you could all guess
what these indices are doing
so to understand the array here let me
remind you
the two means it's a two dimensional
array and the
the entries are tuples of integers and
you can see that
so uh this is these are the various
indices
in this five by three array and
uh we wrote below a neighbor's function
which here for if you have a sort of
three by three
then the neighbors are in the x
direction minus one zero and one and
in the vertical direction minus one zero
and one so
let me just show you a few pieces of
this again i didn't really want to go
into too much detail
here is the julia logo being downloaded
here's the gaussian
filter that i think you'll all recognize
so
this is a function of x and y and by
default we'll use sigma but you can
change it
so by default we can use sigma to be one
half so you could see that this is the
usual
gaussian function right here and we're
also going to allow ourselves
to call this gaussian function with
these indices like the ones you saw
up above so this basically lets you use
indices instead of
directly using x and y just as a
convenience
okay and then we're going to
compute the gaussian filter and here you
can see
we're going to use an s matrix which is
a static matrix
this is a performance hack i don't think
i need to go into this too much
but this will calculate the gaussian
filter in the normalized way
here also we've got some neighbors but
let me go down to the convolved 2d
just to take a look at it basically we
get the neighborhood of every point
and we're going to compute this static
matrix and i just want to point out
some of the pieces because you may not
be so familiar with these
ideas so we have our image it's in
a and we don't want to make a copy
because
copying data is very very expensive so
in fact memory movement i've seen in
other computer science classes people
will count
operations like ads and multiplies but
actually memory movement is a much more
significant matter for most computers
so here what we're going to do is
instead of instead of making a copy of a
we're going to take a view which means
we kind of
have we have this like three by three
sub matrix of a but without making a
copy and we
load it into a static matrix
so and here's the math okay and so when
we do that
you can sort of see what happens when we
filter
we'll do some padding and
the thing that i want to show you most
is
how it's called because this is where
the gpu is most useful
we're going to do this with a broadcast
so what this basically says
is we're going to apply this convolved2d
which is defined at a point
we're going to do it at every interior
point in the image
okay so you can go through this yourself
i'll post this
notebook you will need a gpu a machine
with a gpu if you're actually going to
run this thing
but again i want to conclude
with the most important piece not the
julia code we could kind of go over that
separately
but the real point that the same code
runs on a cpu and a gpu no special
languages
you get that factor of 100 speed up that
you hope to get from a gpu
and the main key difference i mean
there's some double in the details
but the key difference is the cu command
which is going to move the data
from the cpu the central processing unit
down to
the gpu