in this video we'll look at arrays
slices and views
and we'll see what those are in a moment
so arrays are a very common way of study
of storing data of course not the only
way by any means
there are plenty of other data
structures that we can use but so
since they're so important it's very
useful to know how to manipulate them
any in different ways so let's start off
by making a vector
called v and so i'm using the ones
function
to make a vector with containing all
ones
and we see that i can have this
different view by
pressing this arrow it gives me a
vertical view instead and this is the
length of the array so i have
10 ones and we know that we can index
into that array in other words extract
one element using these square brackets
so square brackets three gives the third
element of the array
uh since julia starts indexing at one
the first element is index number one
and we
can modify the array using the same
square bracket so v
indexed at the third element equals two
assigns
the value two to that element and we see
that in that case
v has changed we've made
we've managed to modify the third
element of the array
to give 2. now if we want to extract
a subset several elements of the array
we can do so by indexing using
a range instead so a range is written
with a colon
and v square brackets three colon five
will extract three elements of the
vector
starting at position number three and
finishing in position number five
so this is one reason why one based
indexing where you start and
one is useful because these numbers
exactly correspond to the positions in
the array
and this is called a slice of the array
so when we extract a sub
piece of the array a subset of the array
that's called
slicing now what i what if i want to
modify this slice
how could i do that so you might think
that you could do that
uh just extending the previous syntax
by using v square brackets three colon
five equals four
but if i try and do that i actually get
an error
and uh it tells me that the problem is
that
on the left i have an array but on the
right i have a number
and it doesn't make sense to assign a
number to
an array so we have to actually be more
explicit
we have to tell juror exact julia
exactly what we want to do
what we want to do is assign the number
four to each element of that array
and we can do that using this dot syntax
called broadcasting
so if i do add a dot before the equal
sign i now i'm going to assign
for element wise or element by element
so i'll assign
four to the element number three the
number four and the number five
and when i do that uh we have to check
what happened to the original array
and we see that indeed the original
array got
modified itself so that was
successful and we can also use
uh if we we can also assign
a new array to those elements and if we
do that then
those elements also change okay
so now let's think about well
maybe i want to give a name to this
piece of the array and manipulate
the array via that new name so let's
call w
the slice of v from three to five
so an important question is going to be
what happens if i now
modify the object w in other words
modify i mean
go inside w and change something inside
w
and so just take a moment to think about
what you think this will do before we
carry on
what do you expect to happen and what
might the possibilities be
for for how this behaves so take a
moment to do that
so once we've thought about it we should
just ask julia what it actually
thinks so w looks like an array
and now let's modify the first element
of w
and uh let's look at w and of course we
expected the first element correctly
changed to eight
okay great but but the question is did v
change
right so we took a piece of v and we
called it w
we're now modifying something inside w
and the question is does
v change and the answer is that it does
not
so this is a key thing to remember
when we take a slice of an array and
give it a name
that is actually making a copy of the
data so there's a new copy of those
three elements somewhere else in memory
and w is referring to that copy
and when we modify that copy
of course the original does not get
modified once we know that
this is actually what's happening
okay so yeah so you have to remember
that when we make a slice like this
it makes a copy and and uh it will not
modify
the original array
but of course there might be a case
where we want to be able to
use this new name to modify the original
array so we have to do something
different and let's make what's called a
view
so how do we do that we use this view
function so this is actually a function
in julia
i get i pass in the object
the array object that i want to make a
view of
and again the same range and when i do
that
it looks like you know it looks
from this display it looks the same but
actually it's um we've created an object
of a different type
and we'll look at that in a minute so
now let's modify
z element by element
uh cycle z is this view i gave it the
name z
now and of course zed itself has changed
and the question is now did the original
array view
also change and so here is the array v
and we see that it did change and so
that is the point of a view so a view is
like a window you're looking into
the array well it's even more than a
window because you can actually reach in
through that window
and manipulate the original array so
it's a view that allows both reading
and writing of the original data
so yeah so let's just go come back to
the types if we compare the types of
these two objects w
which was the slice which makes a copy
and zed
which is there's a view then the
original uh
the making a copy makes and the makes a
new type
makes that a type makes an object
making a copy makes an object of the
same type which is just
array but making a view makes this new
type called sub array
we well this whole expression is this
kind of
complicated type of this new object but
we're not going to worry about the
details it's just telling us
exactly what kind of object is
underlying this
new type okay
now you might be frustrated that this
syntax
looks a bit more difficult to use than
the square bracket syntax so julia
actually provides us
with a solution for that so the solution
is to use this
macro called add view so at
is something very special in julia it
indicates
as i said what's called a macro so what
does a macro do it actually takes this
nice piece of syntax that we want to use
and it replaces this expression by a
different expression
so there's actually going to be a video
on macros
uh that you will be able to watch for
more details about this
but basically uh we can think of this as
just literally replacing this
piece of code v three to five with
the other piece of code view of v three
to five
and this will create a subarray object
because it is a view
and then when i modify this view of
course
now we know that the original vector
also gets modified
okay so the same thing works for
matrices as well let's make a small
matrix here
there's a matrix a six by four matrix
and
we can make slices just like we did
before
except now we need to give a range in
the
air in the of rows and a range of
columns
and then it will extract a sub piece but
again
because it's a slice this will be a copy
so you should check
that it is actually a copy i'm not going
to do it and
similarly we can make a view and we can
use the add view macro
to turn a slice into it to make a view
instead and you can see that this is now
a view
so
and finally if we have a matrix we can
think about reshaping it
so this matrix that i created was of
size six by four now let's reshape it to
be of size three by eight which is
has the same number of elements just you
know we're looking at it
and thinking of it in a different way
and the question is
you know given what we've seen so far
you should be
wondering well when i do this reshape is
it making a copy
of all this data or is it a view into
the original array
so that's for you to explore on your own
exercise
for the reader and there's another
useful function called a vect
which takes a matrix and turns it into a
vector so you can see that it's taking
each element
one by one in the matrix in a certain
order and
putting them into a vector so this order
that it's taking them in is actually
reflecting the underlying
way that the matrix is stored in memory
in the computer
the computer's memory is linear it just
has a sequence of boxes in in a
in a row and we have a two dimensional
object so we have to make a choice about
how we actually store that matrix into
memory julia makes one particular choice
called
uh column major so the columns you can
see that it's taking the columns first
it's taking each column it's moving down
the column and putting those elements
into the vector
so again you have to ask is this
function vec
making a copy or making a view
now making copies of memory
copying elements in memory from one
place to another is an
expensive thing to do so we should avoid
it when we can
we cannot always avoid it but when we
can avoid it we should
so you just have to go and check do
these two operations reshape and vet
make copies or make views and you have
to remember that when you use them in
the future
so in summary we just need to be aware
are we making a copy
using a slice or are we making a view
sometimes we need one of those
and sometimes we need the other you just
have to take care
to use the right one