when it comes to computational thinking
it's always good to distinguish between
the theory and the practice at mit we
have the logo
men's a manus literally mind and hands
the mind refers to the theory the hand
refers to
the practice in the context of
computational thinking it's good to
think about
the algorithms the mathematics on the
one hand and how the software is used in
the real world
on the other hand and so with that in
mind because we've been talking about
convolutions
i thought i'd look into how convolutions
are being used in the real world
and so i took a look at uh some image
processing on
software like adobe premiere and i was
also wanted to show you
how it appears in software uh like
machine learning software
and in addition i kind of wanted to talk
a little bit about
the difference between building yourself
versus using a product building yourself
feels good you feel like you're in
control you know every piece of the
puzzle
but maybe no one person can always build
up the most complex software
on their own or maybe they don't want to
or have no time to
on the other hand when you use package
software of course you have the
professional
whistles and bells but you kind of often
lose a lot of control
and so that's something interesting to
think about in the context of
computational thinking
so this is adobe premiere this is video
editing software i'm not particularly
good at it but i started to dabble with
it a little bit
as long as i was making recordings i
thought it'd be kind of good to
see what i could do with it so i've got
my assistant here philip the corgi i've
got a picture of him right here
and i understood that convolutions were
effects that you could play with so i
thought i would try that out
and sure enough if i type convolution in
the effects menu i see all kinds of
convolutions that are preset
all kinds of kernels there's blur and
blur some more find edges gaussian blur
sharpen and so forth and so i thought i
would kind of
dabble a little bit more and i went
ahead and
added the find edges kernel and so here
i'll sort of show it to you
you can see that this little rectangle
here is
basically finding the edges and if you
look at this
if you sort of expand down close you
could see that
the 3x3 matrix listed right here it's
kind of
not really that convenient i guess to
play with the numbers but
here you could see a multiple of of one
two one
and minus one two one and so this is the
kernel that we've been playing in the x
direction
right so this is the this is the silvo
filter kernel that we've been learning
out in class
i happened to watch a video to learn how
to do this
and in the one video i watched the
gentleman pronounced
these nine numbers as m11 m12
m13 these are matrix elements and so
they'd normally be pronounced m11
m12 m13 i guess they would normally be
written with subscripts and maybe that
would have made it more obvious
and of course you can play with these
numbers and you know get a lot of
different things happen you can go ahead
and
make this number much larger it would
wouldn't be so much of an edge detector
anymore
but uh if you would see would sort of
brighten that piece and so forth
so this is the sort of thing i guess you
could play with and what i'd like to
really say
maybe i'll just put it back at 15.
what i'd really like to say is one of
the things i realized is it's very
difficult to
find exactly what this is doing and this
is really my point that
it's kind of nice to go to this sort of
software and have all of these effects
like for example here's this gaussian
blur we can
start making this whole thing much more
blurry so we can start blurring
poor little phillies getting very blurry
now or we can go back and make them
sharp again
so nice user interface perhaps easy to
play with perhaps
you could get the nice list of all these
effects and see what's available to you
but it's not quite easy to know exactly
what's going on if you do things in your
own software
you have that benefit and so there's
that trade-off that i was talking about
here's one more picture i made with
adobe premiere just because it was fun
here is the lobby 7 building of
mit taken from killian court and i just
made this rectangle an edge detector and
also the lawn part over here
in edge detection just to see what it
would look like and i wanted to close
this segment with a few words about
machine learning so these days
you can i think everybody knows that you
can tell an apple from an orange
or an american football from a soccer
ball
or uh even a picture of me from a
picture of you these days
and you might wonder how that goes well
there's convolutions in there
and what happens is there are various
convolutions that will make a bigger
picture
smaller for example one way to do it is
if you
don't overlap the windows a three by
three window
you'll be divide the length and width by
three right and you can keep doing that
make smaller and smaller pictures
so the question is what numbers to put
in those convolutions
so with the sobo filter with these other
filters these are numbers that are
pre-decided
but in machine learning what we're going
to do is we're going to pick the numbers
such that somehow we could tell our
apples from our oranges or our meats
from you so
you're going to run some sort of
optimization that somehow is going to
separate
this image from that image you see and
so convolutions serve for image
processing where you don't even know
what the convolution is
you're going to actually do some sort of
optimization to figure it out as you go