hello wonderful people of the internet
and also mit class 18
s 191 on computational thinking today
we're actually going to be live coding
the seam carving example that was
introduced by grant
a few days ago now if you haven't seen
that lecture please feel free to go into
the description it'll be there and it
gives you a good intuitive description
for what we're doing today
um also while down there feel free to
check out the discord link
where you can leave any comments
questions concerns ideas anything like
that
and hopefully we'll be able to pick it
up during the live stream now
unlike last time we won't be directly
monitoring chat
on stream instead we have the four or
rather three other lecturers available
and you should be able to see them on
the side over here grant allen and dave
and they're able to say whatever they
want whenever they want and they should
be able to interrupt me so
it might be a bit chaotic but hopefully
it'll turn out okay
i think that's all we have to say for
now um so let's go ahead and get started
with a very brief discussion
of seam carving what it is just in case
you missed the last lecture
and you don't want to look at it right
now so
we're going to start with the same image
that we had last week
i don't actually know what it's called
the persistence of memory by dali i
think
but let's pretend that we want to squash
this image horizontally we just want to
make it smaller
in the horizontal dimension now there's
a couple of different ways that we could
do that we could crop the image
like this but cropping has a clear
problem and that you're probably going
to remove important parts of the image
another thing you could do is scale the
image but now all the important parts of
the image become scaled as well
so what could we do well as humans we
can kind of look at this image and we
can kind of see
what we interpret to be important parts
of the image for me i think this
thing is probably important i don't know
what it is but it's probably important
the clock over here probably important
and so if i were to
try to rescale this but keep all of the
important parts
to remain uh with the same aspect ratio
they had before
what i might naively do is draw a line
that misses all of these
important bits of the image and just
remove that set of pixels the idea is
that we want to create a set of
pixels or find a set of pixels that are
so
not important to the image that when
they're removed the user doesn't even
notice they're gone
so for example uh we could create a line
that looks something like this
and again it's just a set of pixels that
can be removed uh without anyone
realizing they're gone now if we were to
go at the top
go through all of the elements at the
top of our image and look for all
possible lines and all possible paths
where we try to avoid all important bits
of the
of the image we might get an image that
looks like this now i'm showing this
right now because it's it's kind of
important
to understand intuitively what we're
trying to miss here so if you look at
these lines they all kind of come
together
and they're obviously missing kind of
the edge here and then it's also missing
the edges over here and the edges over
here basically what we're doing
is we're drawing lines that are avoiding
any sharp
change between one pixel and the next so
again if we were to choose a line and
remove one
and then choose a new line and remove
one and a new line and remove one we'll
actually start to get an animation that
looks something like this
where the image kind of comes together
and you can see that the aspect ratio of
all of the important parts remains the
same
now at some point you start to notice
that there's weird artifacts that appear
and as you keep going further and
further in you'll notice that you know
for example the tree branch up there in
the upper
right hand corner or sorry left hand
corner here probably shouldn't be doing
that you know and the clock doesn't look
right and all this other stuff
but still the fact that you can rescale
and in fact this is called content aware
rescaling in photoshop in this way while
keeping the content on the inside
relatively the same
is pretty cool so now we have i guess
the next obvious question
how does a computer not us tell what is
important in the image
grant talked about this on tuesday the
easiest way is
by finding those edges that i was
talking about before
and one way to do this is with a sobel
filter um
in order to find kind of the change
between two pixels we can put the sobel
filter in there
and this will give us a very brief
highlight over all the edges so
naively what i would probably do is draw
a line that minimizes the intersection
with the white lines in here
and that's kind of the idea behind this
particular method we're just going to
try to find a line
that minimizes the times it passes
through important parts of the image
and it can tell it passes through an
important part because it passes through
the edge of that important part
so hopefully that's clear and we're
going to go ahead and move on to the
next bit i'm going to move this into the
upper
left-hand corner so we have an image on
screen and i'm going to explain what you
see right here let me go ahead clear
this
and let me also open up the file that
we're working on today
so if you look in the upper left hand
corner you'll see an image and this is
going to be
basically the image that we're going to
try to generate uh the
middle terminal here is going to be the
terminal that i'm coding in and the
terminal over here is the typical julia
repl
now because we only have like 25 minutes
and now 20 minutes because you know i
was talking about seam carving for a bit
um i have a bunch of functions that are
already pre-generated
so for example the brightness function
that was introduced by grant a few
lectures ago is here
we have a two additional functions draw
seam and right image
these are just different ways for me to
imprint a seam on an image and output it
easily
and also write a seam out to file
relatively quickly
now when we're thinking about what to do
with seam carving for me
i tend to think of three important
questions the first question is
what is important in the image how do we
find what is important
the next question is how do we find that
seam of elements that's unimportant
and the third question is how do we
remove that seam from the image
so unfortunately due to time constraints
i went ahead and solved
that third that third problem here and
i'll discuss it when we get there
and i've also added a seam carving
function that basically takes in an
image
and then also an output resolution and
we'll squash it down
now if you are familiar with a notebook
all of the logic from the notebook stays
the same
although the terminology may have
changed slightly just because
i'm trying to speak it or explain it to
you as i'm coding
and in that way i change the terminology
to stuff that i would more naturally say
okay so i think we can go ahead and get
started
with the first function which will be to
find the energy
now i do have a reference implementation
over on the side just in case i get
stuck
but hopefully we should be okay so
in finding the energy what first is the
energy well the energy is a term which
corresponds to essentially
this edge this edge image that we see up
here
so i'm simply going to say the energy in
the x direction
energy in the x direction is going to be
equal to
what is essentially the brightness
uh one second the im filter
of the brightness and i'll explain this
in just a second brightness
of the image uh and then we're gonna
have to
um do this with a kernel one second
dot so bill here and we're gonna grab
the x dimension of that
kernel sobel now there's a bunch of
different ways that you could do this in
particular uh
the important bit here is this i am
filter this im filter is basically
replacing the convolve function that
grant showed before
so just keep in mind it's essentially an
image filter it's applying a filter to
an
image now i think that'll work so if i
yank and paste this
and i do energy y i change this to the
first dimension
and then i just say that the we return
the square root dot of
energy underscore x
squared plus energy uh comma y
uh one second squared i think this
should
work so we're gonna go over here and
we're gonna load an image i'm just gonna
call the image image
and um i'm just gonna load zero.jpg it's
just what i called the image
don't ask me why this is just what i did
if i do i am show of the image
we see it up here right so now i'm going
to include the file we just created
and we're just going to run um energy
it's going to be equal to find energy of
image
misbuild sobel let's fix that real quick
and let's try it one more time conclude
and now let's do energy find
energy and now if we do i am show of the
energy
we see essentially the same image we saw
over there to the left
okay so now we're going to get into the
more complicated bits of the lecture
so we've already found the energy now we
have to find something that i'm going to
call the energy
map now what the energy map is is this
image over here that was
green in grant's lecture yesterday but i
just kept everything in grayscale
because
i don't know i like grayscale um this is
essentially
a map of what direction you need to go
in if
you are some random pixel so the idea is
if you're trying to draw your seam and
you have
some random pixel let's say i don't know
maybe up here
right well you're trying to avoid a lot
of stuff underneath you right
so if you're if you find yourself on
this location in your scene
the way you read this map is that you're
gonna go hard right
to avoid any object that's coming in
immediately right so you're gonna go
hard right hard right
hard right until you hit this black
region and then you go down right
the idea here is that this set of pixels
is the minimum possible energy
uh following any path from basically the
bottom up
in order to get to that point so this
means that if you're
i don't know just drawing random path
going up you'll see that
um you'll see that you're passing
through a lot of very
uh very important objects and because of
that we're collecting a lot of energy as
we're going up where we're passing
through a lot of important stuff
and so again the whiteness is kind of
how much important stuff you've gone
through
but i think the thing that everyone i
everyone's eyes are drawn to isn't so
much you know the color gradient or
anything like that
it's actually these little cones of
dunshire or whatever you want to call
them
that appear in the energy map so i want
to take a second to talk about where
those come from
before continuing the lecture so here on
the left we see the energy again this is
your edge detection whatever is
important
i just created a set of pixels that are
along the lower uh the lower bit of the
image
and i said there's a blank pixel here
and here now it doesn't matter what the
value is
we can say they're one or zero it
doesn't really matter uh the point is
that as we're generating the energy the
way we'd read this is for example if
we're at this pixel here
we're trying to find basically what path
will lead us here with the minimal
possible energy right
so basically we could come from this
pixel this pixel or this pixel so we're
going to ask ourselves which one has the
minimum energy
it's obviously this one over here so
what we're going to say is
as we move further up how could we
possibly or what rather what is the
minimum energy we could have when we get
to this point
so if we do this guy here well it has to
come from any of these red spaces
so over here it's also going to be red
and again this was introduced by grant
also
but this is why the cone shape appears
because essentially um the paths can
only
move diagonally upwards or directly
upwards and because of that
it ends up creating these diagonal paths
in the energy map
now what we're trying to do when we
create the energy map is give a specific
pixel that
this guy for example wants to move to so
in this case we know we want to move
down to the lower left
so we're going to say that we want to
move down to the lower left instead of
central or to the right
and so the way i'm notating that is that
negative one is going to be lower left
zero is going to be going towards the
center and one is going to be going
towards the lower right
pixel and so that's how i'm going to be
notating this in the future
okay and like i kind of alluded to here
in order to generate the energy map
literally all we do is set this bottom
layer equal to
the energy and then we just go through
every single pixel
here and we look at all the paths they
could go to and then we sum the energy
up with the minimal path coming up to it
and this will allow us to create this
path in here and also a set of
directions
which looks like this kind of gradient
image in here the way you read this is
that white will be going to the right
black will be going to the left and zero
will be going down so you can see the
flow
of the the seams as they move forward
okay so let's get this done because we
are you know we've got 15 minutes but
it's 15 minutes so the first thing i'm
going to do
is i'm going to go ahead and one second
i'm going to go ahead and define the
energy map which is the thing we're
going to output
as zeros of size of the energy
let me remove that t in there and then
i'm going to say that the energy map
of the very last row and
there is going to be equal to the energy
of
that value as well then under this i'm
just going to say that our set of next
elements
in the notebook this is called
directions but i actually got kind of
confused as to what
that meant so i'm calling it next
elements here which is also probably
equally as confusing
um but here's what we're going to say
we're going to say the next element
is gonna be equal to zeros and
specifically casting it onto an
int of size of energy okay
so now we're gonna say four size uh
sorry i equals
uh and in this case we're gonna start
from the bottom of the image and work up
so we're just gonna say size of energy
along the first dimension minus one
because we already have that bottom row
created minus one all the way up to one
and then we're gonna say for j equals
um one two size of energy
along the second dimension and we're
ending it in there
now we just have to fill in what we said
before so again at every
individual pixel we're looking left
center and right so we have to find the
left most element that we're looking at
i'm going to say left is going to be
equal to max of 1
j minus 1. now the reason the max is in
there is because
we could be hitting the left edge and we
just want to make sure we don't go
beyond that left edge
so similarly right is going to be equal
to the minimum of j plus 1
or the maximum that we could have which
is going to be size of energy
and then along the horizontal dimension
okay so now we have the idea of left and
right and now we just have to find
kind of the local energy the rather the
minimum local energy of the three pixels
underneath us
and the element of that minimum local
energy so we're going to say local
energy uh and then the next element
is going to be equal to find min of
energy map
of and it should be yes i plus one
because we're going one down and
remember that
y is kind of flipped in this way and
then from left
to right uh and i think i need an extra
parenthesis in there
perfect okay so what this will do is it
will return not only the lowest possible
value that could be from the lower path
it will also return the element that
it's supposed to be on but this element
that it will return will either be one
two or three it'll be one of those three
so we're gonna have to modify that in
just a second
so i'm gonna say energy map of ij
is gonna be equal to or sorry i do a
plus equals although
i don't have to because we initialize
them all to 0 so i don't know why i'm
doing that but i'm just doing it
plus energy of i j
and then down here i'm going to say next
elements
of i j is going to be equal to the next
element
uh minus two so again i just wanna be
able to add the next element
uh and it should be so like whatever
element we're on i just wanna be able to
say the next element in the seam
will be whatever we were on plus the
next element so if we do minus two here
it shifts it so it's now going to be
negative 1 0 1 instead of 1 2 3 so you
can just add the next element
directly to it now there's one catch i
have to do here
if we're on if the very left element is
one oop
sorry about the typo there if the very
left element is one
uh we're going to have to add one
because there's only two elements in an
array and it ends up working out
that we have to catch that so we're
gonna say next elements
of i j is gonna be plus equals
one okay so now if we return unless i
failed miserably which i could have
but if we return this it should work so
we're going to return
energy map and the next elements
all right so let's hit it against the
compiler and see what happens include
seems to be fine so now we're going to
say energy map
and next elements it ran that's a good
sign now let's i am show
energy map and hopefully there we go
perfect image exactly what i wanted to
see uh so this is the same energy map
you see over there
and again we can show the next
directions although there's a reason i
left this image on the left hand corner
because the next directions isn't
particularly intuitive for me
uh sorry next elements so james may i
ask
uh you just wrote a double for loop yes
is that
a style question is that the best way to
do it probably not there's probably a
way to broadcast it or something like
that
um or just can you nest can you just
combine the two
for loops uh so
you probably could because uh the way
julia works right is you can actually go
through
obviously i'm explaining this to the
audience not not you but you could
probably just have one big
loop or that goes through all the
elements immediately and then you could
have like
a new index for the inner dimension
along j i just think intuitively it's a
bit easier
to have two separate sets of indices for
one along the x dimension along the y
dimension yeah
i was just wondering if you could just
delete the four put in a comma and
delete one of the ends
oh you want to do this oh wait uh so you
want to do
this so if you do that and then you do
this
is this what you're saying that's what
i'm saying yep and then delete one of
the ends
and also let me i find that easy to read
maybe you know
oh yeah that's fine so let's write that
include that
and then if we run that it should still
be fine so then we include
i'm show energy map and we get exactly
that
except that it's easy to miss on that
line that you have two different
loops basically yeah there's the counter
viewpoint
okay regardless i think we should keep
going we have just a little bit more to
do and luckily the next bit is a lot
easier than it seems
but it seems there's not meant to be a
pun there it's just seems whatever
anyway let's keep going so the next
thing we have to do is actually find the
scene
now i'm actually going to create another
function here which is similar to the
function we have in the notebook
and this is going to be a function i'm
going to call find seem at
okay and the idea here is we're going to
read in the set of next directions
and we're just going to find the seam at
some pixel in the top looking all the
way down to the bottom
so i'm going to say we have the next
elements
and then we also have whatever element
we're going to start on
i'm just calling it element it's
probably a better name but i'm just
going to call it element and
end here okay this is actually
surprisingly easy because again we
already pre-generated
the list of directions each scene will
go at at every pixel
so what we have to do here is simply say
that the seam
seam is going to be equal to zeros of
integer
and again the end's kind of important
because we'll be using this for indices
later
of size of next elements
um and then along the vertical direction
here
uh so the next thing we can say is that
the seam of the first element
of one is going to be equal to just
whatever the element that you're
starting on
is and then here's where the next
element's idea
is is really important so we say 4 i
equal to
importantly 2 because we're skipping the
first element here length
of seam and we go in here and we end
that we're now going to say
seam of i is going to be equal to
seam of i minus 1 plus
the next element um
of again whatever row we're on and then
whatever element in the scene we were on
before it's the seam
of i minus one so this means that we
should be able to just add all of the
next elements together
uh or rather add the next element to the
scene we had before and this allows us
to find the seam a bit easier
and then at the end here we're going to
return the scene
okay so we should be able to run this
right so
i have a function so let's run seam is
going to be equal to
find seam at 100 oh actually
uh i think that was a pre-generated
function so now we're going to say find
seam ah next element not defined that
should be next to elements plural
so now it should run good so what i did
is i generated a seam
starting at pixel 100 at the top and
then working its way all the way down
and so now we have the seam and now i'm
going to use one of my pre-generated
functions which is draw seam
just to draw that seam onto an image and
i'm going to call it image two
it's going to be equal to draw seam
image seam and then we're going to do i
am show
of image 2 and now we see that seam here
and clearly trying to avoid all the
important bits what's nice is looking at
it in comparison here
like i said before if we started this
pixel in here it's going to want to take
a hard right and then weave its way into
this little black area in here
and that's precisely what you see this
seam doing in here so that i think it's
kind of nice that it's doing what we
expect
okay so the last function we need to
write is one that i
naively just called find seam instead of
find seam at it's probably not the best
naming convention but this is just going
to return
the seam the seam of minimal energy
now again because we can read this map
over here as the minimal possible energy
that we could be at at any point in time
so like if we're at this pixel that's
the minimum energy necessary
to get to that point all we have to do
is take that top line
and find the minimum element in the top
line and then we can just draw the seam
corresponding to that
so this should be relatively easy using
the functions we had before we can just
say energy
map and then we can also say next
elements
is going to be equal to find energy at a
find energy map
of energy and then the last thing we
need to do is just say
we have some sort of minimum value which
we don't care about so i'm going to call
it
underscore and then minimum element
number
and this is going to be equal to find
min of
energy map and it should be along the
first
row and then it should be just
everything along the first row
okay uh so now we should just be able to
return
uh find seam at and now we just have to
find the seam at the next elements
and then the minimum element something
like that should work i think let's go
ahead and include
and let's just see what happens if we do
find seam
of energy hopefully it doesn't break
uh doesn't seem to break seems to give
an okay line so now let's just draw that
onto our image again
so image two is gonna be draw a seam
onto the previous image and the seam
and now if we plot that i am showed to
oh
hmm i think that's because i didn't name
it something
yes i need to call this theme and i need
to put an equal sign
one second there we go perfect so now if
we do
image two is equal to draw seam and we
say i'm show image two
you'll see that we have a seam that's
over here on the right edge
now if you remember from the notebook
before this isn't precisely the same
seam
but it's relatively close to the one
that we found in the notebook the
difference might be that our energy
function could be slightly different due
to the fact that we're using a different
convolved function
or something like that so now what i'm
going to do is i'm going to generate
that
entire video that we had before with our
seam carving function again all the seam
carving function is doing
is one finding the energy two finding
the seam and then three removing the
seam from the image and then if we go in
here we should just
be able to run if i did this right seam
carving
of image and then some output resolution
which we're just going to say is 600 or
something for now
um and what i've taken out here is the
ability to write the image i just didn't
want to write it to file because that
takes a bit of time
uh but this will return the last image
so i'm just going to say image
is going to be equal to this and we'll
say image 3 or something and then we'll
run that
give it just a second to do its thing
and then we should have an image that is
smaller than the image that
we had beforehand uh and this should
give us maybe just
one more minute for alan and and friends
to talk about why steam carvings
why we wanted to put it in the
curriculum to begin with because there's
a lot of really cool stuff um related to
this
um and different curricula and julia and
all this kind of stuff so actually
before that i just wanted to make a
comment about julia style so you you
could have
uh called fine you could have used the
same
function name find seem for the two
different versions of the function
you're right theme and find team ad
right you could have just called both of
them fine team
right and then that would have you know
that actually probably would have been
better
um you would create two different
methods right we could do that right now
if we want
yeah um so all we have to do is change
the defined scene
just enables you to think of fewer names
finding names is always hard right yeah
it's just below yeah so if i just change
that to find seam it should work just
fine
uh wherever the two hardest problems in
computer science right it's
finding names of things cache errors and
off by one errors
is that two or three well that's off by
one error that's the joke
oh sorry so anyway here we see uh seam
carving
completely implemented and what is
roughly 25 minutes um
i'm really hoping that this was for me i
find a lot of intuition seeing people
just write things out in code
and also you get to see a bunch of
different coding styles so i hope that
was interesting for you guys
um so yeah alan do you want to talk
about uh real fast and i have to switch
to the uh
to the local students but uh yeah why
did we choose this first of all i just
think this algorithm is cool and that's
sort of like the
that's sort of like the highest order
bit i mean just like that you can do
this so easily is
really cool uh secondly the idea of
illustrating dynamic programming
at an early stage of a computer science
type classes is
is another good thing to do i mean you
have all these paths and yet somehow if
you work your way up by the
magic of computer science you find the
best one it's kind of a little miracle
yup just like that and uh thirdly
and you'll see this in the reminiscing
video if you happen to watch it but i'll
repeat it here in case you didn't see it
which is that
this was a example of something that was
from
uh there there there was a there was a
meeting at mit
figuring out which language to use this
was five years ago julia wasn't ready
yet but
uh they asked about julia at the time
and they said that python was way too
slow for doing this kind of computation
and they
were wondering whether julia would be
able to do it so easily and uh you know
that that is one of the places where
julia shines so he could just do this
everything real fast
you know that is one of the places
there's some echo
yeah okay so
yeah so so that's coming from the other
zoom meeting yeah so i'll just finish
with that since i have to run off
yeah okay so i think this is actually a
good place to stop then uh we'll hop
onto the other meeting with the mit
students
um i guess if there's any last comments
go ahead and say them now
otherwise we'll go
all right great um so thank you guys so
much for coming in have a wonderful day
night afternoon morning evening whatever
time it happens to be your time
and hopefully we'll see you guys around
for the next lecture uh should be next
tuesday
uh should be a lot of fun see you guys
also don't have an end screen so you're
gonna have to see this for two seconds