hi it's alan edelman
and philip the corgi and this lecture is
about structure so to give the idea
let's talk about
matrices you all know about matrices
they're pretty simple objects
they're just m by n tables of numbers
right well no not exactly
wrong well maybe right so the surprise
answer really is matrices are not
necessarily
m by n tables of numbers well you can
always think of them as
m by n tables of numbers but that
doesn't mean you have to store
m times n numbers on your computer to
represent a matrix
so in this lecture we'll talk about
matrix structures and how
we might save storage often using far
less than the m by n numbers
that you might often think of as
required to represent a matrix
so the bigger message here is
take advantage of structure always take
advantage of structure
in this lecture we're going to take
advantage of structure primarily for
saving storage
but we can also take advantage of
structure and maybe we'll see this in
future lectures or you might see this in
future classes you can take advantage of
structure to save time as well
in fact most of the best algorithms and
most of the best
uh computational thinking is about
taking advantage of the structural
problem
so in julia it's often possible we see
this more often than you think
that the structure can be taken
advantage of and
the good news about using julia is
there's no
overhead to using structure in fact you
should it's absolutely recommended other
dynamic languages might
incur some cost but with julia it's
absolutely perfectly reasonable
and often done to represent the
structure go ahead and do it it is
highly streamlined
so what am i talking about let me kind
of
give you the idea by starting with a
vector that shows up in machine learning
it also shows up
in linear algebra in linear algebra it
might be called the column of
the identity matrix in machine learning
it's called the one hop vector
and it's simply this it's a vector that
is all zeros except for one entry that's
one
for example this vector over here has
length six
and the second entry is a one the other
entries are zeros so the one
is the one hot the one is hot the zero
is cold you see
so this is a one hot vector of length
six with the
with the hot element being number two so
if you look at this you'll say well okay
there are six numbers here
but maybe i don't really need to store
six numbers
maybe i can just somehow store two
numbers
and you'd be right if you thought about
it that way so
you can have just the number six which
is the length
and the number two which is the element
that's hot
and somehow the number six and the
number two should be able to represent
that same
object that in your mind is link six
okay you don't
need to store six numbers to have in
your mind the abstraction of something
that has length six and by the way this
is not
about just deleting zeros i mean just to
we could also talk about a one cold
vector so
the the corresponding notion is a vector
that's all ones
except for one entry that's cold right
and so again
you could represent one cold vectors but
with the numbers six
and two if you have a context that it's
one cold
so you don't have to store all those
ones you just need the six and the two
you don't need any zeros or any ones
just the six and the two and context to
say that this is a one
cold vector that's how we build
a one hot object in julia using just two
numbers
so a julia type is created with the word
struct
it's going to be built from two numbers
n and k
that's all that's really going to be in
there is the n and the k and
here there's a little bit of punctuation
in this lesson colon
what does that mean julia's full fill
with all this kind of punctuation
this says that one hat is going to be a
subtype
of an abstract vector of integers
so in simple english we want the one hat
to pretend to be an ordinary vector
even though we're going to store it with
a lot
less information wasting a whole lot
less storage so we're going to pretend
that a one hot is a vector of integers
but in fact it's going to be a one hat
okay so to
create something that has the pretense
you actually need to only define
two functions we need to get the size of
a one hot object
so the size will be the end field of
the one-half object and it's put into a
tuple of length one
because size is always meant to be a
tuple and
let's talk about what should happen when
we type
x of i well when we type x of i
we should simply check whether the
we we only have to check whether the hot
element is equal to i
and so that's exactly what happens here
right we just
check if it equals i okay and so if
i were to create a one hot of six comma
two
as i do here you could see that my one
hot vector
looks just like i
it looks just as if i had typed zero one
zero
zero zero zero it right that's all you
see i can
kind of make it vertical or horizontal
but either way
it is the one hot vector like this now
on the next cell i do a dump of my one
hot vector this lets me see inside
and of course you could see that the
dump shows you
that only the two numbers are being
stored six and two
so don't let the printing fool you well
maybe it's meant to fool you it's
in your mind you could think of it as a
vector of length six right you could
think of it as the
second column of the identity matrix of
a six by six identity matrix
but in fact it is
just stored with the numbers six and two
okay and it might be reasonable just to
kind of
show off because we we actually use this
let's just show you that if
i do take here i guess i'll do it here
if i do take my
my one hot vector
of three it for sure gives you a zero
why because
it says does three equal two the answer
is
false and it turns the false six with
the integer zero
on the other hand if i go on my my one
have vector of two does two equal two
yes true
and we get the one uh i kind of like to
see
these sorts of things um both in
vectorial and
picture format so i kind of like turning
it into an image
so a bunch of colors really so here you
can see here let's let's play with this
as i slide the second slider i want you
to look both
here let's let's move this up a little
i'd like you to look at this vector
and as well as the vector of colors and
you can see it moving
i can make one hot vectors of various
different sizes
right here here i am of size seven
and you could see all the seven
possibilities and so forth just for fun
okay and i guess i don't need that
all right so hopefully you now see the
idea
that a vector or more generally a matrix
or even
any array you don't necessarily have to
store it as a table
to use it as a table so let me show you
a couple more
examples uh so that to completely firm
up the idea
and we're going to use this idea to sort
of get the
key information to be able to compress
images at the end of this uh towards the
end of this
of this lecture so let's talk about
diagonal matrices okay so here's a three
by three diagonal matrix
if you saw diagonal matrices in high
school you might have written it out
with all the zeros
so here's the diagonal matrix 5 6 and
-10 are on
the diagonal okay so there's your matrix
m
but here what i'm going to do is tell
julia
that to convert it to a diagonal matrix
you could of course
directly create a diagonal matrix of
julia
but i've created a general matrix and
i'm going to
now store it as a diagonal maybe it's
good to show you that you could have
directly built
a diagonal matrix with a syntax like
this
and then of course you never would have
wasted memory
in the middle in the middle of this
operation okay but here you see
this is a three by three diagonal infra
matrix
and as you'd expect the amount of
storage is just
three numbers not the nine numbers
so in fact if you take a look if i dump
m you see all nine numbers are being
stored but if i dump diagonal of m
you could see that the basic information
that's being stored are the three
elements
okay so at the risk of repeating the
main message
always look for structure where it
exists if it comes pre-built in julia
like diagonal matrices
then use it if this is a structure
that's
not already readily available in julia
build it yourself
you don't have to ask for permission
that's another main message let's just
go ahead and do it i'm now going to talk
about another commonly used
representation for matrices and that is
the so-called sparse matrix
representation
where we do not store any zeros in the
matrix so this could be a data matrix
perhaps some of the entries are absent
so we think of it as zero
and we don't want to store it or it
could be a numerical matrix which just
happens to have a lot of zeros
and you don't feel like there's any
great use for storing it
so there's the sparse representation and
there's going to be two versions of the
sparse matrix representation that
i'll talk about uh one would be the ij
value or i j a i j representation
and i'll briefly touch on the so called
csc or column sparse compressed
format but i think i don't want to go
into that too far so
first of all here was this diagonal
matrix m with the entries 5
6 n minus 10. and here
is a pretty obvious representation for
the matrix
it's it has the row and column indices
the 1 1 the two two and three three
and the value five six minus ten so this
is what i'm calling the i j
a i j or the uh i j value
representation i'd like to briefly show
you the csc
sparse format it's not the only format
though it's a commonly used one
the csc stands for column sparse
compressed format and i'll show it to
you with this matrix with zero eight
nine five zero zero twelve
zero four so when you uh
when you're represented as a sparse
matrix julia's first choice is the csc
format it's not the only format
but some people think that it's a good
default choice i think that's arguable
as well
so here it is if i dump it there are
the m and n are easy to understand it's
a three by three matrix
and let's see the non let's go skip to
the bottom the non-zero values
are the non-zero values
are uh they go this way five they go
by columns the hence the column format
five twelve
eight nine four you see so these are the
numbers that are being stored
but there's a little bit of overhead
because you have to also
somehow say where these numbers are
located well let's see the row index is
easy to understand
this is in row two this is in row three
this is in row one this is in row one
and this is in row three
so that's easy to understand the column
pointer takes a little bit more getting
used to
but what's going on is it's going to say
which entry starts
with the the column in which position
let's let me let me give it by example
this
this one is going to point to the five
okay this three is going to point to the
eight
the four is going to point to the fourth
element or the nine
and the six is going to point f the six
is basically saying we have now
at the end so the one pointing to the
five
says the five is the first entry in the
first column
the three pointing to the eight says the
eight is the first entry in the second
column right the 3 is the
the second number in the sequence 4 is
the third number in the sequence so we
count the 4 here we get to 9
and 9 is the first entry in the third
column
okay and then finally 6
says we're beyond the end and so we go
here and say it's beyond the end there's
no fourth column
okay so that's kind of what it's
signifying so
i think what's confusing perhaps to some
people
is that this three is in the second
position
here which means that
it's going to point to the second column
but it's going to take the third entry
the 4 is in the third position so the 9
corresponds to the fourth column right
the i hope that makes
sense
okay
let me kind of talk to another kind of
way of compressing information
a little bit different from simply not
storing numbers this is more about like
summarizing numbers okay and we could
think a little bit about
here's a random vector of the million
entries
okay a vector will be good enough for
this purpose here's a random vector with
a million entries
the entries are just digits from one
through nine and you can ask yourself
what do you have to do to convey the
important information
to somebody else what would you have to
communicate what would you have to store
well some people might think that since
the numbers are random you might have to
store
all the million numbers some of you
might have heard of
various ways of compressing the
information in a lossless way
that means that you can store this
there are procedures or algorithms for
example run length encoding
which will store the same information
but with fewer than a million numbers
okay but let me go more extreme and talk
about
statistical information so i'm just
going to
take the mean and the standard deviation
and just for fun pointing out that
because these are random numbers i know
that the theoretical limiting mean is 5
and the
square root of 20 thirds is the standard
deviation
but the main point is that sometimes and
again it depends on context
the mean and the standard deviation is
enough information
from this vector you could throw away
the million numbers now you might say
some people might say throw away a
million numbers well i might need it
someday
well those are the sorts of people that
probably have too much clutter in their
basement
you may need it you may not need it it's
up to you
it requires judgment good judgment as to
whether you need to store the
information
or if you just need to store the summary
okay and just a little bit of julia in
case you don't know what a mean is i
guess everybody knows it's the sum
divided by the length
and the variance is the difference of
uh the data from the mean squared
divided by the length minus one
the length minus one always sort of
confuses people but there's a simple
explanation for it
but the funny thing is it doesn't even
matter uh very often because as long as
your data
is you know not of length one two or
three it probably doesn't matter too
much
maybe you know if it's up you know 50 or
more i don't think it matters
here the the standard deviation by
definition is the square root of the
variance
and so just to show you that we got the
same number
here that was built in with julia but
what i want to do now
is move in into another kind of
compression
a kind of image compression but i'm
going to do it with
numerical examples and i'm going to
start with something
that i think you saw in third grade
maybe in second grade maybe fourth grade
i think you saw it in third grade i saw
it in third grade multiplication tables
okay so here i hope you all recognize
this maybe it brings back memories
here's the 10 by 10 multiplication
table okay it is simply i take every
number i in the i throw and j in the jth
column and i multiply i
times j and that will give me the
multiplication table
while i'm at it let me define an outer
product this is a linear algebra term
but let's just call the outer
product where i can take x times y
for x in v now i'm going to change this
to
i like this sort of math notation i hope
you like it too it's the same as
in but
uh for every x and v and every y and w
let's just do the multiply this would
this would allow us to get general
multiplication tables
so for example what this lets me do is
i can make a little 3x3 multiplication
table or i can go
as far as maybe
a 12 by 12 or
even further so
our co-professor dave sanders tells me
that it's required in great britain
not to stop at 10 by 10 but 12 by 12 is
the
the one that everybody uses in in great
britain so here's the 12 by 12
multiplication
table okay here's another outer product
two four six with ten hundred thousand
just to show you an example
of uh of a generalized multiplication
table
so you see that in the first row we have
two times ten two times a hundred
two times a thousand right or four times
ten four hundred thousand in the second
row
and so on okay so
if you asked how much information there
is in the regular multiplication table
well i think you could see that you
could store
let's make a ten by ten
you can store all hundred numbers
but you also if you have context all you
need is really one number
right the one number 10 right or the one
number 11
and then you just need some context on
how to compute it right so
i don't need like if i ask you right now
okay if i have the billion by billion
multiplication table
and i ask you for the entry that's in
the 5 7 position
you could on the fly tell me it's 35
right you didn't store all those numbers
and look for it
right you just know that the 5 7 entry
is 35 you can compute what you need when
you need it
right so you know you can compute it
just when you need it
right and that's kind of what the point
is you just need to know the number k
right and then when you pick out an
index an element you just need to know
the indices
okay here is a bit more
here's another outer product a
multiplication table if you will
where i suppose it would be a little
harder to see the structure though
you might start to notice it if you get
good at it for example you might
i would say that this number is just
about half this number
when i look at it so this is about half
this is about half oh yes i see
this number is just a little more than
the first number
yep this one's a little more than the
one in the top of its column okay
yeah i'm starting to see it okay or here
if you like you could see a picture
of the outer product of in this case of
a ten by ten
and you start to often get these sort of
striped or maybe
plaid pictures it's not unusual to sort
of see these
plaid pictures when you're taking when
you kind of
show the uh from an image point of view
so
image is you know from zero to one uses
the colors of the rainbow
but then you do get to get these sort of
uh plaid pictures so can we go the other
way
if somebody gives me one of these
generalized multiplication tables like
the array here
can i go the other way and
can i go the other way and and and get
two matrices whose outer product will be
what i need
okay and the answer is you can and
here's a little function
that does it i mean the basic math is in
three lines
you it's very simple really
take if the multiplication table you
take the first column
of your table call it v you take the
first row table call it w
and most of the time you could just take
w divided by v of
1 and that'll give the right answer uh
if you can't divide by zero and if it
was a zero would be all zeros anyway
so you can just do a check for that and
uh i and i think it it just seems like a
good idea to check if
uh you actually get something that's
approximately equal to your table
um otherwise you could tell the user
that the input is not a multiplication
table
and so here for example i took i
factored the outer product of one two
three two two
two and of course i got two four six one
one one
just showing that there's kind of an
arbitrary scaling i mean
i could always multiply this by 17 and
divide this by 17
and i would get the same outer product
and so there's a kind of choice to be
made
right you might think about the fact
that
any multiplication table then could be
represented you might think it could be
represented by
m plus n numbers but in fact m plus n
minus one are sufficient
okay here's an example where i try to
factor a two by two matrix
it's not a multiplication table and my
little error message
kicked in and said input is not a
multiplication table
just as desired just as expected okay
so a multiplication table can be
factored
and stored or possibly never even built
right you could just store the
the factors and that could be good
enough and again
if i wanted the if i have my v and w and
i just want to calculate the i j
entry the moment i need it i can compute
v i
times w j
now what can we do with multiplication
tables well we can add them
right so here's a sum of two
three three by three multiplication
tables right so
if i went from one to one this would be
a single multiplication table
this is the sum of two multiplication
tables here's the sum of three
okay so let's let's just stop with two
and now here's the question can i
actually find
the structure can i find out that this
was made up of two multiplication tables
well interestingly enough there is a
kind of fancy linear algebra
decomposition
which will do this for you okay and my
goal right now
is not to talk about how you can
calculate this thing by hand i don't
want to even explain the linear algebra
you might see it in a linear algebra
class
i just want to mention it it's something
called the singular value decomposition
and it is really good at finding the
multiplication tables
that need to be summed to form a matrix
and the great thing about the singular
value decomposition
is you can choose to throw away
as many multiplication tables as you
like just keep the first few
and this will be a good approximation to
a matrix so
here is the svd of the matrix
the svd of the matrix the singular value
decomposition
always returns a matrix a vector and a
matrix
right so let me put that in here so u
and v are matrices
okay and sigma is a vector
okay they have some special properties
again you might learn about them in
linear algebra
many people like to connect singular
value decomposition to eigenvalues
it's not my favorite approach though
it's kind of
it's a simple thing to do because
eigenvalues appear in every linear
algebra class
so you can kind of sort of dump them in
afterwards
i think that's backwards i think the svd
deserves
its own life and
people get a little too caught up in
calculating by hand i think that's not
even necessary anymore
but again that's a bit of an editorial
that maybe we don't need right now
so let me just sort of show you i'm
going to just show you how to use the
svd for the purposes of this
computational thinking class
but it would be great for you to learn
more about the svd so many things you
can learn
but here i'm going to do all i'm going
to do is calculate the u sigma in v
and then i'm just going to take two
outer products i'm going to take the
first column of u
and then i'm also going to take the
second column of u
as the first argument to my outer
product and i'm going to take the scale
sigma's going to tell me how to scale it
a scaled first column of v and a scaled
second column of v and i'm going to add
them up
and i'm going to notice that this is
somewhat approximately this matrix okay
it actually gets better
for bigger matrices with structure but
here i'll
kind of take a few different cases you
could see that here's a three by three
matrix
here i'm adding two outer products
and you can see that this is not a bad
approximation
okay so it approximates very well i
could add more
for example if you want the exact
reconstruction of the matrix
i would copy this and i would put the
three and of course i could
make this more general and put a sum but
maybe it's good to just see it
right so if i put this in you'll see i
reproduce the matrix entirely
but i could leave out pieces right if i
leave it out again
it serves as an approximation so let's
continue with this
let's see what we can use our svd for
our singular value decomposition
well here's a flag okay
my flag here is an outer product where
it's made up of just ones and twos okay
so here it's an outer
product it almost looks already like a
flag numerically if i use these
distinguishable colors
i think this makes it even look more
like a flag i'm just indexing into
distinguishable colors to make it
kind of visually pretty okay so this is
one outer product
just stripes okay here i'm going to take
two outer products the
just to make it easy i'm taking the flag
plus the flag transpose which means
that i've taken the the the
the flag plus the flag transpose is
really nothing other than and i guess i
could
it's another it's nothing other than
taking the outer product
one way and then
uh switching the arguments which i guess
i could almost
cheat because there aren't that many
entries that are different than the
arguments
by just changing the middle arguments
you see
okay so here's the actual
here here here's the actual matrix and
of course if i take cs
of this by indexing into my colors
i get this picture all right so we might
explore this in the homework that
lots and lots of flags can be written uh
as the sum of outer products
okay thereby saving i mean already you
could see
i i mean you might be able to imagine
doing better than this but
uh i'm not using 81 numbers by any means
to represent this flag
okay well now let's kind of push this
all the way and talk about actual real
images
okay and so here what we're going to do
is we're going to download an image of a
tree
okay so there's a tree and we'll down
sample it a little bit for no you know
just to make it
so you can see it right and so uh
in julia the in the image processing
there's something called the channel
view
which basically takes every pixel and
turns it into its red and green and blue
components
so that by the time you're done if you
turn it into floats which makes it
all the red green and blue is between
zero and one we're going to get a three
dimensional array that's
that's three by two sixteen by three
eighty four so what's going on here is
there the vertical size and pixels of
this picture is 216.
the horizontal size is 384 and the three
represents the three channels the red
the green and the blue
okay we could actually separate out and
get matrices two-dimensional matrices
by using the each slice command in julia
we're going to slice it along the first
dimension the the dimension of size
three
and this will give me the the the red
part of the picture the green part of
the picture of the blue part of the
picture
which i can reconstruct and put next to
each other and you could see it
i kind of like the use of the tree
because you can see very closely that
the
tree is basically green um the green
shows up in the green part
and it kind of looks just like a shadow
through the red filter or the blue
filter
it's kind of it's much black or it's
really is a shadow
okay but anyway there's the three
channels the red green and blue pieces
of the tree picture
okay and what i would like to do is
break up this picture using the svd so
i'm going to take the svd of the red
part the green part and the blue part
remember the u and the v are matrices
the sigma are the scale factors the
the they're the vectors and
let's take a look at what happens if we
try to approximate our tree with one
multiplication table
well there you see the plaid picture uh
maybe
it's as expected you mean the the the
tree kind of sort of smeared to the
to the left and right the trunk kind of
went up and down
you could kind of see the ground that's
sort of being spread to the right
it's pretty much i think what you'd
expect okay now let's kind of move
one over and now we have the sum of two
addition tables right i'm
i'm basically reconstructing this and
i'm summing this and i'm taking up to
two
so this looks like maybe can i call this
like a minecraft tree it's gonna have
that rectangular shape now
with two you can somehow get you can
the tree can sort of become blocked the
ground is a bit more clear
the trunk is still kind of uh
influencing itself all
entirely vertically but we can kind of
continue and go to three and now
the tree can at least have a bit of
staggering now
kind of it's stepped and we can go a
little further
here's the the sum of four
multiplication tables
and so forth so we can keep doing this
after a while you can recognize it
clearly as a tree
but it has some ugly artifacts and we
could keep going a little bit more
remember this tree was what did i say
the size was i mentioned it before
it was 216 by 384 but
probably here you know 60 i guess i
don't completely love those artifacts
but pretty closely you're getting a
pretty decent tree some pictures work
better than others
and depending on what visual quality you
like but it does show you that the
singular value decomposition
is a way of extracting the structure
from an
image it's not the only way a lot of
a lot of image compression schemes like
jpeg they use something different
entirely that's
probably more effective in practice for
images but the svd is certainly quick
and easy and dirty that you can use
it's very easy to use and it is used to
compress
many many things these days so just to
kind of sum it up
in lots of lots of times these days you
have all kinds of data
and if the data could live in sort of a
high dimensional space but it lives on
so the analogy of a plane it's called a
hyperplane then the svd does a very good
job at
compressing the information to the
important pieces
this is the idea behind something you
may see in statistics called
principal components analysis and it
also
is some it gets generalized into machine
learning where
you pick out the small number of
parameters
you