what are macros we've seen several of
them already they start with the at
sign so what what is going on well they
are a way
to take a piece of julia code and
actually transform it
into a different piece of julia code so
we're actually
representing julia code itself as
an object inside julia so let's see how
to do that
so let's use as an example this function
called peak flops
when you run that it actually does a
little calculation using matrix
multiplication and tries to estimate
how fast your computer is how many flops
or floating point operations per second
your computer can actually run at
so what we want to do is measure how
long that operation took
so we're going to do that using this at
elapsed
macro so elapsed just means how much
time
a certain operation took but we're using
this
macro that is defined in julia uh
in order to do this so when we run that
we see that
well this particular operation took 0.33
seconds
it is no longer returning the output of
the peak flops function itself
instead it somehow sort of diverted
that and is now returning instead the
time it took to run the function
so this at sign is actually a visual
clue
that something strange is going on so
what julia did is take
this piece of code and transform it into
a different piece of code
that actually calculates the time it
took to run the function instead of
returning the output of the function
itself
at macro expand is itself a macro we
know that because it begins with the at
symbol
and what it does is just shows me the
code that that macro is producing
so here we see well it looks pretty
complicated but that's because it has
these extra
information which is the line numbers
where the code is actually coming from
inside the julia code base we want to
get rid of those because they're pretty
noisy
so we'll use this remove line nums
function from base from base julia which
takes the piece of code that's being
generated and removes these line numbers
so what we see is that indeed the
original code is still there
but julia has added extra
pieces of code around it would take the
current time in nanoseconds
and then they run it runs the function
and produces the new time in nanoseconds
afterwards and subtracts the old time
so this strange var is just a
local variable with us an automatically
generated name
and you can see that we're dividing by
10 to the nine because
uh we're getting the time in nanoseconds
and we want to return the time in
seconds
so julia has actually when we run this
at elapsed peak flops
julia is actually replacing the call to
peak flops with this new piece of code
and that is what is getting compiled
that's how
macros work
so how is julia able to manipulate these
expressions
which are representing julia code
so let's look at that so if i type x
equals one plus two
one plus two is a piece of julia code an
expression
but what julia is doing is actually
evaluating that expression
so it's turning the string one plus two
into a julia code object and then it's
evaluating that
in the normal way but if i want to
actually go and manipulate
that piece of code i don't want to
evaluate it or run
that code i just want it as an
unevaluated piece of code
and that's what an expression is and i
can make expressions in one of two ways
i can either so we call that quoting the
code
i quote the code i sort of put it in
quote marks
uh so that julia knows not to evaluate
it but
instead of quote marks which would make
a string i use this
colon parenthesis or i can
use this quote end construction and so
either of these make
expressions you can see that when i use
quote end it actually adds
some line number information in so this
again leaves this expression alone
without evaluating it and returns the
unevaluated expression
so let's actually see what type of
object i've produced when
i do that i produce this type so
expert with a lowercase e is the name of
the variable
which corresponds to this expression
that i defined
whereas extra with a capital e is the
type
which is a type that julia finds to
represent its own
expressions so for example let's create
this expression y
plus one so because it has the colon
parenthesis we know that that is going
to create an expression object
of course if we evaluate this piece of
code y plus 1
in the normal way using julia that would
will give an error because
in this notebook we have not defined a
variable called y
but so i'm really seeing that this
is giving me the unevaluated expression
and it's perfectly fine
as a piece of julia code even though y
is not defined
because this is a julia object i can go
and use the standard julia tools to look
inside and see what
what is in there so let's use the dump
function
which just takes an object and tells me
what all the sub
pieces inside that object are and so
here we go this is the output so we see
that this
expression three variable is of type
expression with a capital e
and that consists of a field called head
which is call so we know that it's some
kind of function call
and then the and then another field
called args meaning
arguments so those are the arguments of
the call the first
argument is the plus is a symbol
so a string a kind of string
which is just the unevaluated plus sign
and then the second argument is the
unevaluated
symbol y it's like a the unevaluated
string
y and the third argument is one and so
that is the way that julia is
representing
this piece of code and we know
from the video on types that we can
extract the fields
ourselves manually using dot so extra3
dot head
gives me the symbol call and extra3.x
gives me an array with these three
things inside
but now the point is that i can actually
go and modify those myself
so i can extract the second argument
which is currently y
but because that's just a standard julia
array with some kind of objects inside
i can actually go and modify the second
argument and when i do that
okay it allowed me to do that and now
let's look at extra three
and we see that it actually changed and
so this is how macros work
they receive their input as julia
expressions and then they're free to
modify them however they want
of course you might think this is
dangerous and that's why macros always
have this at
symbol so that we know visually that
julia is allowing whoever wrote the
macro to modify my code into a new piece
of code that might do something
different
so for example in pluto the at bind
macro
actually what does that do it binds
a julia variable to some html
object which is for example a slider so
that's a
you know complicated thing to do and the
macro is hiding the
details from me but i can always go and
look at the source code of the macro to
see exactly what's going on
so this isn't this is the start of
what's called meta programming
so programming sort of one level up
where i'm actually writing a program
which itself modifies a program so
modifies julia code
normally pro the programs we've written
so far actually modified data
but now we're writing a program that
modifies a program
and that's a very powerful but can be
dangerous tool
and so it should only be used in certain
circumstances and we're not going to
teach
how to actually make a macro but they
can be very useful when you need to do a
syntactic
transformation transform the syntax of a
piece of code