so now that we have types we want to be
able to write functions
that act on those types so for example
we want to write
a width function which can take a
rectangle object and return me its width
but i don't want the width function to
work on a complex number or an integer
so how can we do that we actually write
a function like this
width of r but i give this type
annotation
this type annotation operator is this
two
colons next to each other our colon
colon rectangle
means that this width function takes one
parameter called r
and that r has to be of type rectangle
for this particular
version of the width function so then
it's just a standard function definition
in julia
here i've used the short form of a
function definition
and then i can run that on this r
object and i see that it returns its
width but if i try and run that function
on for example the number three then i
get an error it tells me there is no
method that matches
with and here you see colon colon in 64.
in other words there is no version of
this function which
can receive a single integer because i
have not defined
any method that does that and so that is
the way that you can prevent
people calling your code with objects
that do not
belong in there on the other hand it's
very common in julia
to have specialized versions of
functions that work on certain types
and general or generic versions that
work on any type
so as a simple example let's think about
a function called area
we know how to calculate the area of a
rectangle it's its width times its
height so let's define that here it is
and we're using a type annotation to
make sure that that version
only works on a rectangle in particular
the object that we're passing in
must have fields called width and height
for this code to even run
but we're also defining another method
where we do not have a type annotation
that means that this code will work for
any
input value that i give it except for
rectangles so
because the method that we just defined
has a more specialized type signature in
other words the sequence of types
which i put into the function is called
signature
julia will realize that when i pass in a
rectangle it should call that more
specialized version
but when i pass in any other object it
will call this general version
so for example if i call it on my
rectangle it correctly multiplies the
width and height and calls the first
method whereas if i pass in just an
integer
it will just return that same value back
to me of course that's not necessarily
ideal either for example area of the
string hello
will return hello so you could complain
well area should only be defined
maybe for numbers for example and you
can specify that in julia as well
so what we're seeing is if i just write
area
i can ask what is the function area and
it's telling me that it's
what's called a generic function so a
function which can have
many methods and in this case we have
two methods
so each of these versions of the
function is called a method
and if for example we later created a
new type called
circle then we would also need a
specialized method of the circle where
it knew that the area should be pi r
squared for example
it's perfectly fine to define that new
type
and a method for the area function when
i define that new type
and when i pass in a circle object it
will actually call
that correct method just note that in
pluto
right now as of this recording you
actually need to put
all the methods of a particular function
together in one cell between
begin and end people often mention
multiple dispatch
when they talk about julia this is a
very key
concept in julia so what does that mean
dispatch is just this process that we've
been describing
where you choose a different method or
version of a function
depending on what the input types are
and multiple dispatch means that you
actually
look at all of the input types for all
of the arguments of your function
to choose which method or version to
call so let's look at an example of that
let's define a complex number cc
three plus four m that's how we define
complex numbers in juliet
i am m stands for imaginary part
so that's basically what i would write
in mathematics as 3 plus 4
times i i being the square root of -1
or some engineers use j in julia we use
m so that we don't take over the symbol
i so that you can use i and j in your
program
and here we're taking three plus four
times m and that gives me a complex
number
and now let's look at how to add
complex numbers so if i do cc
plus cc i get the new complex number
uh 6 plus 8m as i should but how do i
know
what julia is actually doing when it
does that
so i can use this macro at which
and type this put give it this
expression cc plus cc
and it will actually tell me which
method of the plus function
it's calling so plus in julia is just a
normal function
it just has a lot of methods defined in
fact currently
it has 184 methods to find
i can also define new methods of plus if
i define my own types and we'll
see that later in the course we can
actually look
how do you define the sum of two complex
numbers in julia
it will actually give us a link to the
source code so i'm going to click that
link
this takes me to the source code of the
version of julia that i'm running
and it tells me exactly how julia
defines the sum of two complex numbers
so here it is the sum of a variable
called z which is of type complex
and a w which is of type complex is oh
i'm going to make
a new complex number and i'm going to
take the real parts and add them
and take the imaginary parts and add
those and put those inside my complex
number that is
the definition of the sum of two complex
numbers
in julia but you'll see that if i now
add a real number to a complex number
instead
there's a different method that does
something different and actually if i
add
them the other way around i also have to
define that that's
another different definition and you can
go and find out what exactly it's doing
so defining types in julia is a very
common thing to do
and it's very useful and you see from
this notebook
that the point is that we can actually
make
different objects that behave in
different ways
they can have different functions that
i'm calling
even though internally they might have
the exact
same information but i can actually now
specify
that difference to julia and allow it to
call different functions and do
different things