hello today i'm going to talk to you
about different programming environments
you can code julia in
but first i'm going to start at kind of
a weird place the question
why is programming difficult to me
there are two reasons why programming is
hard first is
writing the code itself understanding
the programming logic like how for loops
work
why exactly print line works the way it
does multiple dispatch all of this kind
of stuff
the other challenge which i think is
actually even more difficult at least
for beginning programmers
is running that code on your own machine
the reason i think this
is because when i started to learn to
code you know quite a few years ago
i found that i could genuinely
understand most of the programming logic
the textbook was trying to teach me
i understood loops i understood
conditionals i understood basically
everything that i needed to do i could
write the code
i just couldn't figure out how to get it
to run and i tried so many different
things and i could not figure it out
the textbook was trying to get me to use
some sort of ide that i genuinely didn't
understand
it wasn't until i opened up a terminal
and i learned that i could compile code
in that terminal
that i actually learned how to write
code properly and to me
being able to run code in that terminal
and being able to look at the file that
i'm typing and write it in my own text
editor was essential for me
understanding code
itself so this brings me to my main
point
different programming environments make
running code easier for different people
and different people gain intuition by
writing code in different ways so now we
want to talk a bit about what
programming environments are available
and to me there are three general
classes the first
is basic text editors the next are
integrated development environments or
ides which i alluded to earlier
and the last are notebooks now text
editors are usually the simplest to set
up
examples are vim nano notepad plus plus
basically
anything that you can write the code in
save it to file
and then run it separately links for
more information about all of these text
editors will be in the description but
essentially it doesn't really matter
what text editor you use you could
technically use microsoft word if you
wanted to
the point is you just write the code run
it separately now integrated development
environments have
loads of features it's essentially
combining the text editing step
with the running step now when i say it
has loads of features what i mean is
that integrated development environments
are usually what people use when they're
writing large software projects
so it has things like code completion
usually git integration so you can
version control your code
a bunch of other things for our purposes
we're going to be calling both vs code
and atom integrated development
environments for julia there used to be
another project called juno but i think
the juno developers are combining their
work into vs code soon
the point is that both of these could be
considered text editors with additional
features instead of
true integrated development environments
and trust me my twitch chat was really
really keen on pointing out the
difference between these
but i generally consider any environment
that combines both the editing step and
the running step into one
as an integrated development environment
and so we'll be showing these off in a
bit
finally the third programming
environment is also the one we've been
using the most for this class
and those are notebooks these are really
good for classes because they're
essentially markdown text with code in
built into it that you can run
which is really useful for a number of
different purposes and the notebooks
that most people use for julia
are pluto.jl which we've been using
again mostly for this class
and also jupiter at this point i think
it's worth showing an example
for all of these different editors so
first of all i'm going to be showing a
very simple vim
example what you're seeing here is me
writing a full script in vim
with twitch chat on the side i'm writing
an example that's available in the
algorithm archive for generating a
sierpinski triangle
as you can see here there's a bunch of
different plugins to vim that allow for
you to have syntax highlighting and a
bunch of other things
but this is generally the flow you write
code in one terminal you run it in
another terminal
like i said it's the easiest thing to
set up so it shouldn't be too difficult
to pick up as long as you can understand
the text editor that you're using
now vim is not necessarily the text
editor i would choose for beginners but
it's what i use and i like it a lot
so now i'm going to show you the general
workflow for visual studio
this is significantly different than
what we did with vim in that you can see
way more of the code what i'm showing
you now is the klima project the climate
machine project
that i do for work and i'm showing you
how you can kind of use some features
in visual studio to make it easier to
parse large code you can open up your
own terminal and run whatever code you
want in your terminal
if you want julia to work with visual
studio it's really important that you
get the right plugin specifically for
julia which i'm showing off here
now another point about visual studio is
that we will be having a short mini
lecture on how to use visual studio
specifically with julia
in the near future so keep that in mind
we'll be doing this again soon
and finally notebooks we've already
talked a lot about notebooks for this
course
so my assumption is that you already
know how to use them again please feel
free to check fonz's lecture if you want
more information there
so again bringing it all back together
different programming environments work
better for different people
and you as a programmer need to figure
out what environment works best for you
if it is genuinely a notebook then use a
notebook if you like ides use that
if you feel like you're best suited just
writing code in a terminal and compiling
it kind of like i am
then do that instead you just need to
make sure you're comfortable in whatever
you're coding in that's the most
important thing