in julia we can define our own types
so why would we want to do this and and
how do we go about it
so let's think about a rectangle
it has a width and a height two
different
numbers that we need to describe the
rectangle similarly a complex number
has a real part and an imaginary part
and a position vector
in two dimensions has also two
components
in each of these cases we could
naturally describe
the object by two numbers in a tuple
or a pair and in julia we could do this
also as a as a tuple just by writing
three comma four
in parentheses and so we could literally
write rectangle equals three
four three comma four to mean that the
width was three and the height was four
similarly c equals three comma four
could mean
we were going to interpret that to mean
that the complex number
is three plus 4 times i
but it's clear that there's a problem
here because we're not telling julia
this is a rectangle 3 4 and this is a
complex number
with 3 and 4. somehow we need to give it
that extra information
because for example we might want to
take the width of a rectangle
but we don't want to be able to
calculate the width of a complex number
so this is why we need to be able to
define our own types
we want to define a rectangle type right
how do we do that so what does it mean
to define a type
a rectangle type should reflect the fact
that object
of type rectangle should have a width
and a height that belong to them
we should be able to access those
variables and talk about
an actual object being of type rectangle
and that is a kind of schema or template
for
what all rectangles should look like and
then we want to be able to create
object which follow that pattern
and we should be able to create
different objects which have their own
data inside and we're going to call
those fields of the type
and so this is the way that julia allows
us to construct
new types we use the struct keyword
which is
short for structure and we give the name
of the object
in this case rectangle and we always
will use a capital letter at the start
of the type
name and in fact at the start of each
word in the type name
if there are several words and then we
will give a list
inside this definition of each field
name
that we want and which type we want that
field
to be so in this case we're saying that
there is a field called width
of type float64 and a field of height
which is also of typeflow 64.
these types don't have to be the same
it's just in this case they are
we could have height which was an
integer for example that's perfectly
fine
and so this is telling us what the
template or schema of this object
is we now want to create objects of that
type
which we do by using the same type name
as if it were actually a function name
so
here you can see that i'm using the type
name rectangle
exactly as i spelt it before and i'm
using it as a function and i'm passing
in the values which i would like to
store
inside the object so when i do that i
actually
create an object r which is a rectangle
if i click on this triangle we see that
the rectangle
contains the width field which has value
1.0 and the height field which has value
2.5
so we can say that i have created an
object which is called
r r is a variable just as if it were an
integer
but r is actually of type rectangle and
inside
r there are these two values stored
so if i do type of r it tells me that
it's a rectangle
i can also say r is a rectangle
which tells me is r of that type or not
i can go in and extract information from
the object
using r dot width for example or
r dot height the dot operator here is
saying
extract the field called whatever comes
after the dot
from the object that comes before the
dot
and of course now we can also create
another object r2
is also a rectangle with different
contents
3 and 4 in this case and so this is a
separate rectangle so there's one
rectangle living over here another
rectangle living over here
and of course they have different
heights and widths the height and width
being stored inside
the object so i like to think of these
objects as boxes or bags
which contain this data and you can kind
of go in and
pull out the data from that object and
you can pull
out the data from that object and those
data have names i can say oh
ah please give me your width and then r2
please give me your width
so we often call these types composite
types or composite types
because the information is being put
together
into this bag or aggregated they're also
called aggregate types we're collecting
lots of disparate or distinct pieces of
information which may be of different
types but they all somehow belong
together
and they describe one object now that we
have these objects we might want to
modify them so maybe my rectangle for
some reason changed size
so what can i do about that well i might
want to go in
and try to change the width of my
rectangle so let's try and set the width
to 10
by just going in and changing this field
and what i find is that
i get an error it's telling me that the
rectangle type is
immutable it is unchangeable i cannot
modify
the fields of this object and so that
is a choice in julia that by default
structs
or composite types are actually
immutable
unchangeable unmodifiable and the reason
for this is that that often leads to
faster code
of course there is a way of making a
type which is mutable
you do that by writing mutable struct
instead of
struct so go away and try that make a
new struct
with a different name and try and modify
its fields and you will be able to
so that is of course sometimes something
that's useful to be able to do
but immutable structs are much more
common
in julia and much more useful